<add><doc><field name="id">chi.67160761</field>
<field name="author">Hawaii. Public Utilities Commission</field>
<field name="author2">Hawaii. Public Utilities Commission</field>
<field name="sdrnum">sdr-chi3539035</field>
<field name="sdrnum">sdr-umn9933147080001701</field>
<field name="oclc">1773156</field>
<field name="language">English</field>
<field name="language008_full">English</field>
<field name="format">Serial</field>
<field name="format">Journal</field>
<field name="htsource">University of Chicago</field>
<field name="author_top">Hawaii. Public Utilities Commission</field>
<field name="author_sortkey">hawaii public utilities commission</field>
<field name="mainauthor">Hawaii. Public Utilities Commission</field>
<field name="title_sortkey">annual report</field>
<field name="title_display">Annual report</field>
<field name="title">Annual report</field>
<field name="titleSort">Annual report</field>
<field name="title_ab">Annual report</field>
<field name="title_a">Annual report</field>
<field name="title_top">Annual report.</field>
<field name="serialTitle_ab">Annual report</field>
<field name="serialTitle_a">Annual report</field>
<field name="serialTitle">Annual report</field>
<field name="topicStr">Public utilities</field>
<field name="topicStr">Public utilities Hawaii</field>
<field name="publishDate">1913</field>
<field name="countryOfPubStr">United States</field>
<field name="record_no">100627658</field>
<field name="date">1913</field>
<field name="Vauthor">Hawaii. Public Utilities Commission</field>
<field name="Vtitle">Annual report</field>
<field name="enumPublishDate">1917</field>
<field name="volume_enumcron">v.5 1917</field>
<field name="bothPublishDate">1917</field>
<field name="vol_id">chi.67160761</field>
<field name="ocr"> &apos;6 COMPLAINTSFORMAL. Il. Investigation of the formal complaint of Emil C. Peters vs. Mutual Telephone Company, was commenced October 2, 1917. The evidence disclosed that subsequent to the issuance by the company of its telephone directroy for October, 1916, Mr. Peters instructed the company to alter his office telephone connection, furnishing him two lines instead of one as formerly used by him. The company assigned to him in addition to the number 1115 theretofore held by him, the number 1303. These numbers were not shown in the new directory issued in April, 1917, at all. They were also omitted from the classified business list. On October 27, petitioner requested an order from the Commission commanding and directing the company to &quot;forthwith print or cause to be printed on separate stickers the telephone numbers, name and business address of petitioner and mail or deliver same to all persons and corporations who and which were in April, 1917, and were then, subscribers to the Mutual Telephone Com- pany.&quot; The relief prayed for was denied on the ground that in view of the fact that a new directory would be published in Novem- ber, 1917, by the Mutual Telephone Company, the order prayed for would be unreasonable. PUBLICATIONS. Following is the list of publications for the year 1917: Publication No. 16-Report of Investigations in the matter of the Investigation into the affairs of the Ho- nolulu Gas Co., Ltd. No. 17—Report of Investigations in the matter of the Investigation into the affairs of the La- haina Ice Company, Limited, of Lahaina, County of Maui, T. H. No. 18–Laws relating to the Public Utilities Com- mission of Hawaii. No. 19—Report of Investigations in the matter of the Investigation into the affairs of the Ko- hala Telephone Company, of Kohala, County and Territory of Hawaii. No. 20—Report of Investigations in the matter of the Investigation into the affairs of the Maui Telephone Co., County of Maui, Territory of Hawaii. &apos; &quot; THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO LIBRARY &quot; &quot;&quot; &quot;13 EXHIBIT &amp;quot;C.” PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION FUND, DISBURSEMENTS—1917. Month Salaries Investi. gations Printing and Ad- vertising Law Books Office Supplies Rent Postage Furniture and Fixtures Inci- dentals Totals 5.05 $ 5.00 2.80 64.00 196.25 371.75 75.00 75.00 75.00 150.00 1.00 6.00 11.25 56.36 13.50 20.35 297.51 329.04 162.87 313.24 1,312.33 January February March. April. May. June. July August. September. October.. November December $ 455.00 837.78 585.59 620.00 588.36 1,675.00 545.96 925.00 825.00 760.48 663.71 625.00 55.75 148.00 14.95 63.30 7.00 26.45 108.75 30.00 67.93 9.75 29.05 11.80 16.70 1.50 8.00 4.00 1.00 3.00 1.50 10.00 2.00 5.08 4.06 22.73 44.18 24.91 5.00 100.90 15.10 6.58 466.05 1,312.04 1,261.93 1,306.06 1,100.11 3,343.91 623.14 1,457.89 937.25 1,225.85 1,300.48 1,763.03 87.45 165.00 4.00 12.50 31.60 164.64 508.00 1,002.00 150.00 75.00 150.00 75.00 75.00 18.78 26.87 13.25 14.50 10.00 Total. $9,121.38 &apos; $4,177.08 | $ 718.75 / $ 233.59 $ 385.68 $ 900.00 $46.00 $ 316,30 $ 198.96 $16,097.74 &quot; &quot;9. Act 238. An Act Conferring Additional Powers Upon the Public Utilities Commission of the Territory of Hawaii. Be it Enacted by the Legislature of the Territory of Hawaii: Section 1. That in addition to the powers already conferred by law upon the Public Utilities Commission of the Territory of Hawaii, the said commission is hereby authorized and directed to investigate charges made by all corporations, copartnerships or persons for water supplied to consumers for domestic uses and purposes, in cases where the water thus supplied is secured by virtue of a lease or leases from the Territory of Hawaii, re- quiring rates to be fixed by the licensee with the approval of the commissioner of public lands of the Territory of Hawaii. And in the event it shall appear upon such investigation that the water thus supplied to consumers for domestic uses and purposes is by virtue of a lease or leases requiring rates to be fixed by the licensee, with the approval of the commissioner of public lands of the Territory of Hawaii, then and in that event the said com- mission shall report to the said commissioner of public lands the result of such investigation, and whether the rates charged to consumers are reasonable or not. Section 2. In the event said commission investigating as hereinbefore provided, shall report that in its judgment the rates charged to consumers for water supplied to consumers for do- mestic uses and purposes, are not reasonable, it shall be the duty of the attorney general of the Territory of Hawaii to take appro- priate action to secure for such consumers reasonable rates for such water, or, should he be so advised, to proceed to cancel the licenses and leases of the corporations, copartnerships or persons charging such unreasonable rates. Section 3. This Act shall take effect from and after the date of its approval. Approved this 7th day of May, A. D. 1917. LUCIUS E. PINKHAM, Governor of the Territory of Hawaii. &quot; &apos;8 after the date of its approval by the governor of the Territory of Hawaii, (30th day of April, A. D. 1917) subject, however, to the approval of congress to be secured within two years from the date of such approval by the governor. Act 165. Public Utilities Commission. An Act to amend Section 2221 of the Revised Laws of Hawaii, 1915, as amended by Act 170 of the Session Laws of 1915, Relating to Public Utilities Commission. Be it Enacted by the Legislature of the Territory of Hawaii: Section 1. Section 2221 of the Revised Laws of Hawaii, 1915, as amended by Act 170 of the Session Laws of 1915, is hereby amended to read as follows: “Section 2221. Number, appointment, of commissioners. There is created a public utilities commission of three members, who shall be called commissioners and who shall be appointed in the manner prescribed in Section 80 of the Organic Act for terms of three years, or the unexpired portions thereof, so that the term of one member shall expire on the thirtieth day of June in each year, beginning with the year 1914; provided, however, that no member of said commission shall be a salaried officer or employee of the Territory or any political subdivision thereof. One member shall also be appointed chairman of the commission. The members of such commission shall serve without remunera- tion, except that they may be allowed their reasonable traveling and other expenses while proceeding to, attending and return- ing from attendance at meetings of the commission, or reason- ably incurred in the discharge of their duties. No person own- ing any stock or bonds of any public utility corporation, or hav- ing any interest, or deriving any remuneration from any public utility shall be appointed to or hold any office on the commission, or be appointed or employed by the commission.&quot; Section 2. This Act shall take effect from and after July 1, A. D. 1917. The foregoing bill, after reconsideration of the veto of the Governor, was upon a vote of two-thirds of all the elective mem- bers of the House of Representatives and a two-thirds vote of all the elective members of the Senate of th Territory of Ha- waii, made a law on April 28th, 1917. &apos; &quot;PUBLICATION No. 26 Fifth Annual Report of the I Public Utilities Commission of Hawaii.) v 11 For the Year 1917 OF HAWAII 1900 TERRITORY HU KE. EA.O- KAMINA• I•KA:P HONOLULU: HAWAIIAN GAZETTE CO., LTD. 1918 &quot; &quot; &quot; &quot;TABLE OF THE PUBLIC UTILITY CORPORATIOND COLLECTION OF FEES. Name of Corporation f 1% ross Due 1917 1/50 of 1% on Capital Stock Due Sept., 1917 Total Assess ments and Collections 7.74 15.33 2.96 1.67 9.33 7.96 6.82 9.66 17.49 0.14 $1,000.00 60.00 100.00 20.00 30.00 320.00 600.00 5.00 $ 3,295.48 410.66 305.92 103.34 78.66 1,295.92 2,693.64 69.32 54.98 1,902.26 RAILROAD AND TRANSPORTATION COMPANIES. Oahu Railway and Land Co...... Kahului Railroad Co.... Kauai Railway Co.. Hawaii Railway Co., Ltd. Koolau Railway Co.... Honolulu Rapid Transit &amp;amp; Land Co... Inter Island Steam Navigation Co., Ltd. Oahu Shipping Co., Ltd.. Matson Navigation Co.... Hawaii Consolidated Railway Co., Ltd.. TELEPHONE CORPORATIONS. 730.99 Mutual Telephone Co... Hawaii Telephone Co... Kohala Telephone Co... Kauai Telephone Co., Ltd. Maui Telephone Co.... LIGHTING COMPANIES. Hawaiian Electric Co., Ltd. Hilo Electric Light Co., Ltd. Waipahu Ice &amp;amp; Electric Co., Ltd. Lahaina Ice Co., Ltd... Waiahi Electric Co., Ltd. Island Electric Co., Ltd. Honolulu Gas Co., Ltd. W. 0. Crowell. 1.36 2.76 2.87 6.69 6.71 123.11 30.00 2.00 4.00 10.00 568.94 195.52 9.74 21.38 53.42 200.00 58.56 5.41 14.03 1.01 3.37 2.26 3.10 2.18 0.05 2.00 13.40 90.00 830.82 185.18 2.02 6.74 8.52 53.00 363.36 2.10 Totals.... 11.99 $3,399.06 $12,441.92 &quot; &quot; K 300 #47 P19A3 5th. 1917 Hawaii(Ter.) Public Utilities Commission. Annual report. &quot; &apos;5 of the Commission to the Supreme Court of the Territory of Hawaii, but made no attempt to take advantage of the statutory provisions providing for a stay of the order appealed from. The Company failing to obey the order of the Commission, the Com- mission obtained an injunction restraining the Company from violating the terms of the order. The Supreme Court of the Territory of Hawaii reversed the order of the Commission on the ground that the Commission was without jurisdiction over the rates of the Company, exclusive jurisdiction over the rates and charges of the Company being in the Shipping Board created under the provisions of Act of Con- gress of September 7, 1916, known as the Shipping Act. ( In the matter of the Investigation of the Inter-Island Steam Naviga- tion Company, Limited, 24 Haw. 136.) COMPLAINTS/INFORMAL. 1. Investigation of the complaint of Edward Scharsch vs. Inter-Island Steam Navigation Company, Limited, was begun February 26th, 1917. Mr. Scharsch made a claim for loss of goods shipped on the steamer &quot;Mikahala&quot; on December 22, 1916. The loss in question occurred by the swamping of one of the boats of the “Mikahala&quot; in Nawiliwili harbor. In was shown for the Inter-Island Steam Navigation Company, Limited, that under the terms of the bill of lading under which the goods were received by the company for transportation, the company was ex- empted from liability from losses resulting from &quot;disasters or dangers of the seas.&quot; The investigation by the Commission ended March 21, 1917. 2. Investigation of the complaint of Kalihi Taro &amp;amp; Land Company, Limited, vs. Mutual Telephone Company was begun December 28, 1916. Kalihi Taro &amp;amp; Land Company, Limited, complained that the Mutual Telephone Company had cut its wire or telephone connection for failing to pay bill against the com- pany for the months of November and December, 1916; and the company further complained that the Mutual Telephone Com- pany had not notified it of the intention to cut the connection. The undisputed showing of the Mutual Telephone Company was that the regular routine for delinquent subscribers had been car- ried out, delinquent notice having been mailed to the company during the latter part of November. As no payment had been received up to December 25th the telephone was disconnected on the 26th. No basis for complaint being shown, the complaint was disallowed January 10, 1917. &apos; &quot; Hawal Publicatiothes LER COM PUBLICATION No. 26 Fifth Annual Report of the Public Utilities Commission of Hawaii For the Year 1917 OF HAWA! 1900 TERRITOR ALU KE. ER- OKA AINR Onodamas HONOLULU: HAWAIIAN GAZETTE CO., LTD. 1918 &quot; &apos;11 EXHIBIT &quot;A.&quot; RECEIPTS, PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION FUND. .Balance in hand... Interest $ 9,463.70 Semi-annual fees. .Interest .Semi annual fees. .Interest . Semi-annual fees. .Interest Semi annual fees.. .Interest 1917 Jan. 1,.. 31. Feb. 28. Mar, 31. Apr. 30. 30. May 31. June 30. July 31.. Aug. 9. 31. 31. Sept. 30. 17.50 13.71 5,062.88 1,158.08 15.48 19.98 36.68 13.50 13.50 347.47 11.20 4,658.47 13.66 1,188.02 17.41 15.75 14.26 30. Oct. 31 31 Nov. 31 Dec. 31. 66 1917 Total Receipts.... $12,644.55 Total . $22,108.25 &apos; &quot; cnicago U OT REQUEST * Patron Name google1 Transaction Number 3212790 Patron Number Item Number 67160761 K 300 H47 P79 A3 5th 1917 Title Annual report. Pickup Location Date/Time Nov/15/20 JUN 14 1972 THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO LAW SCHOOL LIBRARY CHICAGO, IL SU &quot; &quot; UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO 67 160 761 D &quot; &quot;7 No. 21-Uniform System of Accounts for Telephone Companies Designated as Class “A.” No. 22-Fourth Annual Report of the Public Utili- ties Commission of Hawaii for 1916. No. 23—Report of Investigations in the matter of the Investigations of the Inter-Island Steam Navigation Company, Limited. ACCIDENTS. Following is a list of the fatal accidents investigated by this Commission during 1917 as required by Section 2223 of the Re- vised Laws of 1915: Name of Company Date Name No. 17 12 Hawaii Consolidated Ry., Ltd... Hawaiian Electric Co.. Honolulu Rapid Transit &amp;amp; Land Company Inter Island Steam Navigation Company, Limited. 8-30 8-2 7-6 8-24 1-8 1-8 1-27 2-21 3-5 3-28 7-24 10-30 12-6 8-18 2-19 4-17 2-7 4-2 6-6 8-31 9-7 9-18 Lindsey. Miller.. Kapule.. Kahalekiu. Morimoto. Yoshikawa. Kawawhilo.. Devereaux. Anehila. Nystrom. Shintaro. Meyer. Kaholoi. Murikama. Shumabukoro. Sawa... Kusesch. Silva... Donaraski. Opunui... Shingara. 6906 6977 283 284 297 304 306 314 342 405 414 24 2 3 76 86 97 124 131 133 Kahului R. R. Co...... Koolau Railway Company, Ltd... Oahu Railway &amp;amp; Land Co.... LEGISLATION. Laws of the Territory of Hawaii : Act 134 Electric Franchise, Hamakua. An Act to Author- ize and provide for the Manufacture, Maintenance, Distribution and Supply of Electric Current for Light and Power within the District of Hamakua, on the Island and County of Hawaii, Terri- tory of Hawaii. This Act to take effect and be law from and &quot; &quot;15 EXHIBIT &amp;quot;E.&apos; SCHEDULE OF ACCIDENTS. Name of the Company Minor Serious Fatal Total 4 ii 7 3 528 95 2 1 1 1 1 2 9 Hawaii Consolidated Ry., Ltd.... Hawaiian Electric Co... Honolulu Rapid Transit &amp;amp; Land Co... Inter Island Steam Nav. Co., Ltd.. Kauai Telephone Co.... Koolau Railway Co.... Kahului Railway Co. Honolulu Gas Co., Ltd. Mutual Telephone Co. Oahu Railway &amp;amp; Land Co.. Oahu Shipping Co..... 12 4 541 112 2 3 8 1 W 27 79 2 1 1 6 7 33 93 7 &quot; &quot;2 Koo er enq A3 ang 7! PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION OF HAWAII. WILLIAM T. CARDEN, Chairman. A. J. GIGNOUX, Commissioner. W. P. THOMAS, Commissioner. A. BOSTLEMAN, Secretary. WATSON &amp;amp; CLEMONS, Attorneys. H. GOODING FIELD, Auditor. Offices: 414, 415 and 416 Kauikeolani Building, Honolulu, Hawaii. Telephone 4791. &quot; &quot; &quot; &quot;10 EXHIBITS. Attached hereto and made a part of this report are the follow- ing exhibits: Exhibit “A”-Receipts, Public Utilities Commission Fund; Exhibit &amp;quot;B&amp;quot;–Table showing how fees were assessed and col- lected : Exhibit &amp;quot;C&amp;quot;--Segregation of disbursements; Exhibit “D”—List of hearings; Exhibit &amp;quot;E&amp;quot;-Schedule of accidents. Respectfully submitted, PUBLIC (&apos;TILITIES COMMISSION OF HAWAII, By WILLIAM T. CARDEN, Chairman. BY ALEX. J. GIGNOUX, Commissioner. &quot; &quot;4 on September 1st, 1917, Miss Charlotte MacAuley was appointed Assistant Secretary for the Commission. Her resignation was accepted to take effect December 31st, 1917. MEETINGS. The Commission has held 39 regular meetings and 21 specia! meetings. It has conducted 20 hearings; 4 adjourned meetings were taken for lack of a quorum. A list of the hearings is hereto attached, marked Exhibit &amp;quot;D.&amp;quot; INVESTIGATIONS. 1. Inter-Island Steam Navigation Company, Limited. Investigatons of the Public Utilities Commission of Hawaii was begun on August 24, 1916, for the purpose of considering Passenger Tariff No. 2 and Freight Tariff No. 2 of the Inter- Island Steam Navigation Company, Limited. This investigation was a general one into the affairs of the Company and not merely a hearing on specific complaints. The Commission, therefore, went thoroughly into the entire opera- tions of the Inter-Island Steam Navigation Company, Limited, as a public utility corporation and as a result of this thorough investigation, a state of affairs was disclosed that affected not only the specific complaints made to the Commission, but the en- tire rate schedule of the Company. On September 1st, 1916, the Company issued a new freight and passenger tariff, raising certain of the theretofore exist- ing charges for the carriage of freight and passengers, which raise in rates in the opinion of this Commission was unjustified, unwarranted and unreasonable, and the Commission so found. The Commission ordered the Inter-Island Steam Navigation Company, Limited, to reduce all charges for the carriage of passengers and freight to not to exceed the rates and classifica- tions which were in effect on the 1st day of August, 1916, and rates to take effect on or before October 15th, 1917. The Commission also found that the difference between quan- tity rates and less than quantity rates in the Company&apos;s tariff was unwarranted, unreasonable and unjust. The order of ilie Commission was issued requiring the Company so to amend its freight tariff that shippers of less than quantity lots should in no case pay more than the mininmum charge for quantity lots. The Company noted and perfected an appeal from the order &quot; &quot;Report of the Public Utilities Com- mission for the year ending December 31, 1917. Honolulu. T. H., January 2, 1918. Honorable Lucius E. Pinkham, Governor of the Territory of Hawaii, Honolulu. SIR:-In compliance wth Section 2223 of the Revised Laws of Hawaii, 1915, the Public Utilities Commission of Hawaii re- spectively submits herewith its report for the year ending Decem- ber 31, 1917. MEMBERSHIP. On January 1st, 1917, the personnel and staff of the Public Utilities Commission of Hawaii was as follows: Chas. &apos;R. Forbes, Chairman; A. J. Gignoux, Commissioner; William T. Carden, Commissioner; H. P. O&apos;Sullivan, Secretary; E. M. Wat- son, Attorney for the Commission. The following changes in the personnel of the Commission oc- curred during the year. On June 25th, the resignation of Chas R. Forbes having been accepted by the Honorable Lucius E. Pinkham, Governor of the Territory of Hawaii, Mr. Forbes hav- ing accepted a commission as Major in the United States Army Reserve Corps, William T. Carden was appointed Chairman and William P. Thomas was appointed Commissioner in place of Mr. Carden. The following changes in the staff of the Commission occurred during the year. On March 1st, Messrs. Watson &amp;amp; Clemons were appointed counsel for the Commission in place of Judge Watson. On August 25th, H. P. O&apos;Sullivan was given a vaca- tion from August 25th to December 1st, 1917. His resignation as Secretary was accepted to take effect December 1st, 1917, Mr. O&apos;Sullivan having accepted a commission as an officer in the United States Army Reserve Corps. On July 17th, Mr. H. Gooding Field was appointed Auditor for the Commission, and &quot; &quot;13 --- f Month Jaruary.. February. March. April... May June. July 05 ,04 .93 (06 111 .91 4,14 89 .25 185 1.48 1.03 7.74 &quot; &quot; &quot; &apos;! 14 EXHIBIT &quot;D.&quot; LIST OF HEARINGS. Date Company Place Feb. 1917 8. Inter Island Steam Navigation Co., Ltd. Honolulu 28. 66 66 66 66 Mar. 8. 14. 15. May 3. 7.. 10. 16. 21. 28. 31. June 4.. 8.. 13. 18. 66 6 66 66 22 66 22. Oct. 22. 23. 20 Hearings. &apos; &quot;&quot;</field>
<field name="allfields">&quot;Hawaii. Public Utilities Commission Annual report. [Honolulu] v. 1st- 1913- Mode of access: Internet. Public utilities Hawaii. CHI CHI 20220419 google chi.67160761 v.5 1917 1917 pd bib US serial item date &amp;lt; 1927 UMN UMN 20220501 google umn.31951d02621172n 2nd 1914 1914 pd bib US serial item date &amp;lt; 1927 UMN UMN 20220501 google umn.31951d02621171p 1st 1913 1913 pd bib US serial item date &amp;lt; 1927 UMN UMN 20220501 google umn.31951d02621173l 3rd 1915 1915 pd bib US serial item date &amp;lt; 1927&quot;</field>
<field name="rights">1</field>
<field name="ht_heldby">hawaii</field>
<field name="ht_heldby">stanford</field>
<field name="ht_heldby">uchicago</field>
<field name="coll_id">1021850194</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">BLANK</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">IMPLICIT_PAGE_NUMBER</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">CHAPTER_START</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">BACK_COVER</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">TITLE</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">FRONT_COVER</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">FIRST_CONTENT_CHAPTER_START</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">IMAGE_ON_PAGE</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">UNTYPICAL_PAGE</field>
<field name="ht_scanning_order">left-to-right</field>
<field name="ht_reading_order">left-to-right</field>
<field name="ht_cover_tag">follows-reading-order</field></doc></add>