<add><doc><field name="bothPublishDate">1863</field>
<field name="bothPublishDateRange">1860-1869</field>
<field name="language">English</field>
<field name="rights">1</field>
<field name="format">Book</field>
<field name="titleSort">Bay State Forty-Fourth : a regimental record</field>
<field name="date">1863</field>
<field name="publisher">M.O. Hall &amp; Company,</field>
<field name="enumPublishDateRange">1860-1869</field>
<field name="title_a">The Bay State Forty-Fourth</field>
<field name="enumPublishDate">1863</field>
<field name="htsource">Library of Congress</field>
<field name="lccn">03009977</field>
<field name="title_sortkey"></field>
<field name="author">Safford, De Forest,</field>
<field name="callnosort">E513.5 44th .S</field>
<field name="title_display">The Bay State Forty-Fourth : a regimental record / ed. by De Forest Safford ...</field>
<field name="topicStr">United States</field>
<field name="topicStr">United States. Army. Massachusetts Infantry Regiment, 44th (1862-1863).</field>
<field name="topicStr">United States History Civil War, 1861-1865 Regimental histories</field>
<field name="ht_cover_tag">follow-reading-order</field>
<field name="allfields">The Bay State Forty-Fourth : a regimental record / ed. by De Forest Safford ... Boston : M.O. Hall &amp; Company, [1863] 32 p. ; 23 cm. Articles and verses written by soldiers at the front. Cover-title. Mode of access: Internet. United States. Army. Massachusetts Infantry Regiment, 44th (1862-1863). United States History Civil War, 1861-1865 Regimental histories. Safford, De Forest, ia.baystatefortyfou00saff LOC ILOC 20130810 ia loc.ark:/13960/t05x2js29 1863 pd bib US bib date1 &lt; 1928 ia.cu31924030906964 COO COO 20171128 cornell-ms coo1.ark:/13960/t6c25gh3d 1863 pd bib US bib date1 &lt; 1928 </field>
<field name="oclc">9951274</field>
<field name="title">The Bay State Forty-Fourth : a regimental record</field>
<field name="publishDateRange">1863</field>
<field name="publishDateRange">1860-1869</field>
<field name="author_sortkey"></field>
<field name="callnumber">E513.5 44th .S</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">COVER</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">COPYRIGHT</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">RIGHT</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">TITLE</field>
<field name="ht_page_feature">LEFT</field>
<field name="ht_scanning_order">left-to-right</field>
<field name="sdrnum">sdr-ia-loc8197292</field>
<field name="sdrnum">sdr-coo3789490</field>
<field name="era">Civil War, 1861-1865</field>
<field name="title_ab">The Bay State Forty-Fourth : a regimental record</field>
<field name="coll_id">0</field>
<field name="author_top">ed. by De Forest Safford ...</field>
<field name="author_top">Safford, De Forest,</field>
<field name="countryOfPubStr">United States</field>
<field name="Vauthor">Safford, De Forest,</field>
<field name="record_no">009580119</field>
<field name="title_c">ed. by De Forest Safford ...</field>
<field name="language008_full">English</field>
<field name="title_top">The Bay State Forty-Fourth : a regimental record /</field>
<field name="ht_reading_order">left-to-right</field>
<field name="author2">Safford, De Forest,</field>
<field name="publishDate">1863</field>
<field name="Vtitle">The Bay State Forty-Fourth : a regimental record</field>
<field name="vol_id">loc.ark:/13960/t05x2js2</field>
<field name="id">loc.ark:/13960/t05x2js29</field>
<field name="ocr">^ 
 
 prige;^ 1. 15 CT&amp; 
 
 li- 
 
 [^ 
 
 n 
 
 ^ 
 
 m 
 
 f\ 
 
 ® 
 
 gim^tilal ^^coifS. 
 
 EDITED BY 
 
 DB FORIZST SAFFORD;p 
 
 OF THE 44TH REGIMENT 
 
 BOSTON: 
 M:. O. HEALL &amp; COMIPAISTY, 
 
 NO. 23 CORNHI LL. 
 
 Mo- 
 
 W. F. SROWN &amp; CO. PRINTERS,Vj/,H.C&gt;' NO. 15 CORNHILL, BOSTON. v 
 V 
 
__EMPTYOCR__EDITED BY 
 
 DE FOREST SJlPFORD;, 
 
 OF THE 44TH REGIMENT 
 
 BOSTON: 
 
 m:. o. mall &amp; coi^xi?A 
 
 NO. 23 CORNHILL. 
 
 ,v-CT^,- 
 
 W. F. BROWN &amp; CO. Pr7nTERs\5/4jL^ NO. M CORNHILL, B03T0 
 V 
 

 4.^^oV 
 
MARCH, 186 3. 
 
 OUR BOYS. 
 
 TT would be quite foolish, as well as useless, to boast that the 44tb 
 J(i contained the only young men of promise that have enlisted since 
 the war began ; or to claim that "our Regiment" is in advance of all 
 others in education or morality ; nor is it the intention of the writer of 
 these few pages to employ them as the medium of boasting in regard to 
 this thousand ; — he wishes merely to make mention of the thoughts that 
 occur to one who has simply met our boys as comrades in camp duty or 
 on the march. 
 
 Tlie love of fun is an element in the character of most boys ; and in 
 the 44th that characteristic seems a marked one. We mean genuine 
 fun, without the desire for mischief that very often accompanies the ele- 
 ment mentioned. The mock dress parades and kitten burials that made 
 some rainy days at Readville pass more quickly, weje evidences of the 
 humor of the ring-leaders there ; and, at the present time, whenever 
 there is an opportunity, something laughable is brought forward to en- 
 liven the crowd. 
 
 On the voyage to Newbern, in spite of the actual discomforts expe- 
 rienced, we enjoyed many a hearty laugh, and had good cause to thank 
 the originators of the jokes perpetrated. To ventilate the space assigned 
 us between decks, a " win's'l" was extended from a point above the up- 
 per deck to the lower, the opening to which was just above the boys* 
 heads. The stairway from deck to deck being very slippery, those pas- 
 sing up or coming down quite naturally grasped a fold of the wind-sail to 
 prevent a fall ; and the consequence was, that the air intended for the 
 conipSiies below had but an imperfect passage. Here was a chance for 
 a disagreement ; and the subscriber stood looking on, imagining that 
 nothing could prevent hard words, at least. All at once the cries of, 
 1 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 " Do let go," " Come, you must be careful," " Just let that alone, please," 
 ceased. There was a dead calm. The stairway was crowded, and the 
 ventilator of no more use than a tarred rope. Suddenly the unfortunate 
 man that happened then to have his hand upon the canvas, was saluted 
 with a roar from a dozen in chorus, uttered with all the strength of 
 healthy organs of voice: "Let go that Ventilator!" The chief 
 and leader, the most furious, apparently, in gesture, was a thoroughly 
 good fellow, a graduate of Harvard, whose pleasant countenance and 
 entertaining conversation always gathers a group about him. The 
 novel method of thus concentrating the force of a dozen in one stentorian 
 yell startling enough to nearly frighten a man to death, was not without 
 its effect on the minds of the irritated sufferers below, and ill-humor fast 
 disappeared as the shout was continued. 
 
 On our first expedition we encamped in Washington near a box fac- 
 tory, well supplied with lumber, wliich we made use of in constructing 
 bunks for the night. Until about two o'clock, the following morning, 
 the 44th rested quietly ; but a number of the boys of one company wak- 
 ing up rather chilly at that time, gathered about the fire which was burn- 
 ing rather low. " Who was going after wood ? " was the question. Now 
 when a soldier, or civilian, has got a place at a poor fire, even, the sensa- 
 tion of some degree of warmth is given up reluctantly, and the man 
 that volunteers to get the fuel is self-denying indeed. The fires needed 
 replenishing — the bunks were of wood, could be easily taken to pieces, 
 and burn they must — never mind the occupants, — indeed it would be a 
 mercy to wake them now, and have them come to the fire ; they couldn't 
 sleep much longer (?) — and at it they went ! In one instance the owner 
 was too far in the land of dreams to be awakened by a slight cause, so 
 that the boards were removed, his gun and equipments were put out of 
 sight, and the ruins of the little shanty blazed at his feet before he 
 waked up. In perfect bewilderment, he commenced to run, supposing, 
 no doubt, that he was in the hands of Southern " patriots." The hearty 
 peal of laughter that followed his movements, soon brought this victim 
 to his senses ; and suddenly realizing his ludicrous position, he joined in 
 the merriment with a will. 
 
 We have among us some rare fellows that we would not exchange for 
 their weight in gold, on account of the moral influence they exert. 
 When soldiers have been marching the whole day through a swamp, and 
 at dusk are not in sight of the camp, you may be sure some cheering in- 
 fluence must be exerted to prevent a feeling of depression. Let our 
 readers imagine themselves standing ankle-deep on the muddiest road 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 they ever travelled, having in their minds no cheering thought of dry 
 clothes, clean stockings, slippers, and a seat at the fire when they get 
 home. Fancy, then, the disagreeable chilly feeling that must be expe- 
 rienced, and think whether you would expect,—" Happy are we to-night, 
 Boys," « Viva la Compagnie," or any other live-giving song ! ^Te°all 
 remember distinctly the place and the weary feelings that were coming 
 upon us, when our noble comrades cheered the whole left wing for an 
 hour with songs of pathos and mirth. The " Old Mountain Tree " sung 
 there in that dismal swamp, had a greater charm than ever ; this was 
 one of the scenes never to be forgotten. The anxious friends who 
 search the newspapers for the slightest reference to our boys, and who 
 ask God's protection for them in storm and battle, can be comforted with 
 the thought that the sick or wounded in any part of the whole army, 
 will receive no greater attention and kindness from comrades, than the 
 members of the 44lh from each other, as far as lies in their power. 
 With this mention of the kindly feehng and care for those connected 
 with them it may be as well to close this paper. At some other time, 
 doubtless, a readier pen than mine may describe to you particular ones 
 of the Regiment whose noble qualifications or good deeds render them 
 favorites ; whoever writes it can do no more than justice to " Our Boys.'' 
 Newhem, Jan. 12, 1863. Xliv 
 
 DEATH OF ASTRONOMER mTCHELL. 
 
 " He is seat for to the Presence." 
 
 One more ! and this the noblest of the And as he knelt at the poor victim's side, 
 
 T ;i.„ ♦) ■ 1 , " '^^ ^^^'^'^ cars a sound, to his a son"- " 
 
 Like the grand star that guards the Came from the concave in a mi-Wity dde 
 
 sku-ts of night, Lo ! from his loiterino- sec him speed 
 
 Could he not stray above our murkv plain alon-— ^ 
 
 Till the fair day-spring bless our aching His' mantlelind his faith to all of us be- 
 
 That beam millennial which salutes " 
 
 T ^1 ? t',""' •, , He died where pois'nous weeds and nois- 
 
 Inexorable I^.tc the beam will hold oned hearts ^ 
 
 VV 1th equal hand, and show our scale Stifle the life of body and of soul ; 
 
 Tu^y ^^ V^ ' 7 , From the cursed realm all loveliness de- 
 
 Tho youth, and strength, and wealth are parts u io\tiiiRss ae 
 
 r^r^^J'^^^^' l''}^u^~ , ^s '^"■•Is and flowers fly from the icy 
 
 Genius must follow yet, and mingle with Pole. " ^ 
 
 ^'^'^ ^■"''^- Rush to the rescue of the old control ; 
 
 Ti. f . , , Through fire and blood redeem each liill 
 
 His feet were 'customed to the Milky and dell. ■ 
 
 n„u;I?^-\ ,, , , ., ■'^'"l ^^''^''i tliis dread sirocco hence 
 
 On his high errand l;e but turned aside, shall roll 
 
 Like old Samari^a's Traveller, to stay (Onward or backward) to its native hell 
 
 1 he blood and tears abandoned by vile Aharon's unfading rose shall floS 
 
 ^ "'^^- where he fell ! 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 THE FIRST EXPEDITION. 
 
 TuK following account was written for the Janesville Daily Gazette, by our jolly Post- 
 master, Mr. Fish. One might know, from his verj' appearance, that he would keep 
 anybody's turkey after getting it once into his clutches — he must eat if he lives. 
 
 JPN ray last letter, I could only give you an account of the setting out 
 [j of the expedition under Maj. Gen. Foster, and the mo.^t probable 
 rumor as to its destination and object. I under-estimated the number of 
 our troops, but now that I have learned it, I do not feel at liberty to 
 state the exact foi'ce. It was divided into three brigades, commanded 
 by Cols. Stevenson, Lee, and Araory. We waited in Washington from 
 Friday noon until Sunday morning for the artillery and cavalry, whose 
 march had been impeded by the burning of a bridge by the rebels. 
 
 We began our march at daybreak, Sunday morning, Nov. 2d. About 
 six miles from AYashington our advance met the rear guard of the 
 enemy. One of our cavalry had his horse shot, and was taken prisoner. 
 About five o'clock in the afternoon the rebels made a stand near a small 
 creek. The battle, or perhaps more properly, skirmish, was begun by 
 the artillery. Two companies of the 44th Massachusetts were ordered 
 forward. The firing of musketry was kept up only about a quarter of 
 an hour. The remainder of our brigade, Col. Stevenson's, was then 
 ordered to advance. The column halted just as our company reached 
 the middle of the stream. We stood in the water above our knees just 
 forty minutes. The rebels had got our range, and the grape-shot and 
 shell began to strike uncomfortably near. The old soldiers tell us that 
 our position was a trying one. We could not see the enemy, or use our 
 pieces ; we could only stand and listen to the shot and shell plashing in 
 the water about us. The shell striking in the stream did not explode. 
 
 We at last marched forward slowly, lying in ambush a part of the 
 time. Our skirmishei's were endeavoring to find out the position of the 
 enemy ; they were not very successful. About one o'clock we found 
 ourselves drawn into an ambuscade. We had halted opposite rifle-pits, 
 and the rebels poured in a volley at a distance of not more than ten 
 yards. At the first musket report our oflicers gave the order, " Down ! " 
 This was all that saved us from being cut to pieces ; none were killed, 
 and only three wounded. Our second lieutenant received two balls in 
 the leg ; both wounds, however, were slight. 
 
 The artillery was immediately posted in an open field on our left, and 
 
commenced a brisk cannonade. The 24tb and 44th Massachusetts were 
 drawn up in line of battle in their rear. The firing of the artillery 
 presented a splendid spectacle to the new troops. It afforded an im- 
 mense feeling of relief, after our surprise, to watch the shells by their 
 burning fuse, as they went screaming through the air, to burst and carry 
 death and destruction into the ranks of the rebels. The guns were well 
 manned, and the firing very rapid ; a hundred and sixty shot and shell 
 were thrown from the sixteen pieces. The rebels acknowledge a loss of 
 sixty killed and wounded. They retreated in such haste as to leave a 
 part of their slain on the field. Our loss was three killed and six 
 wounded. We lay down on our arras at two o'clock, wet and weary. 
 "We had been on the march twenty-two hours, with only an hour and a 
 halPs halt at noon. 
 
 The next morning, I went to a house a quarter of a mile from the 
 field to get water. I found no one at home but an old woman and her 
 two daughters. She said her two sons and her daughters' husbands 
 were in the rebel army; they were obliged, to go without having a 
 chance to stand a draft ; the officers came and took them. I asked her 
 if she was a secessionist. She replied, *' I go for my country ; those 
 who will not fight for their country are too mean to live — they ought to 
 be killed." I told her we Avere fighting for our country, our whole 
 country, south as well as north. To this she replied, " I don't want to 
 talk any more about it ; ive believe what the men say" There is a wood 
 deal in that reply ; the people of the South believe what their leaders 
 tell them, and it is surprising to see what a unity of sentiment there is 
 here. It is said there is still a Union feeling in North Carolina. I 
 don't believe it is very extensive. I took pains to talk with every white 
 man I met on the march. I found but two unconditional Union men. 
 A prominent citizen of Plymouth told us there were but four Union 
 men in the place ; the others only pretending to be, in order to save 
 their property. All along our march we found most of the private 
 dwellings deserted. They carried off all their property which could 
 easily be removed. Much of what remained was carried off or destroyed 
 by our ||:oops. The order was given to the men to take all the provis- 
 ions they could find. The people who remained at home and professed 
 Union sentiments were protected. 
 
 The morning after the battle we marched to Williamston. None but 
 negroes were left to welcome us. The soldiers were allowed to break 
 into the stores and houses ; considerable property was destroyed. PIts, 
 geese, turkeys and chickens, however, were the principal sufferers. 
 
6 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 Your correspondent, equipped with a long pole, made a gallant charge 
 upon a fine flock of turkeys, and had just made a good fat one bite the 
 dust, when a man with shoulder straps on appeared at the back-door, 
 calling out at the top of his voice, " Did'nt you know these were officers' 
 quarters ? Drop that turkey ! " A breakfast of hard crackers and cof- 
 fee, taken in connection with a seven miles' march, had the effect of 
 causing me, for the moment, to forget the world-wide difference between 
 an officer and a private. I was so inconsiderate as to suppose one 
 needed dinner as well as the other ; therefore I didn't heai" the order, 
 " drop that turkey," but carried him oflf in triumph. The dinner of 
 " our mess " that day was something to date from. Think of a common 
 soldier dining on roast turkey, sweet potatoes, and honey ! 
 
 One of the objects of the expedition was the taking of a fort at Ham- 
 ilton, a small town on the Roanoke. The fort was built on Rainbow 
 Bluff, an eminence so high above the river as to be out of the reach of 
 the gunboats. The enemy did not attempt to hold the fort. A large 
 part of the town of Hamilton was burned by our troops. The flames 
 of its church and school-house lighted us on our march through it. 
 From Hamilton we marched to within six miles Qf Tarboro. The 
 reason of our not advancing farther, was probably owing to the fact that 
 the enemy were strongly reinforced, so as to greatly outnumber us ; 
 they had railroad facilities for transporting troops from Richmond. 
 
 "We marched back to Plymouth, where we took transports for New- 
 bern. The expedition occupied just two weeks. It was fruitful in 
 forced marches and discipline to the men. The new regiments bore it 
 well, although some days many were obliged to fall to the rear. 
 
 Nov. 15, 18G2. 
 
 EXTRACTS FEOM A DIARY 
 
 KEPT ON THE LATE EXPEDITION TOWARDS GOLDSBORO. 
 
 Thursday^ Dec. 11. At 7 o'clock this morning, our regiment^started 
 from the parade ground, on an expedition to some place unknown to any 
 of us boys. By 10 o'clock we had joined the other regiments of our 
 brigade, and also the other brigades, and at this hour our entire force, 
 numbering somewhere in the neighborhood of 15,000, including cavalry 
 and artillery, went " marching along," with Gen. Foster for our leader. 
 Our progress this forenoon was slow ; but this afternoon we moved more 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 rapidly. The load we carry with us — knapsack, gun, and all our equip- 
 ments — is estimated to be about thirty pounds ; this, in addition to bad 
 roads and rapid marching is felt by us all. At 8, this evening, after 
 having marched about twelve miles, we were drawn up in a large field, 
 and gladly obeyed the order to unsling knapsacks; and throwing them 
 upon the ground we proceeded to the building of camp-fires. This is 
 comparatively an easy task, inasmuch as rail fences abound in this vicin- 
 ity ; and, when the rails are placed in a proper manner, they make an 
 excellent fire. Our fires were soon blazing, and the dippers of water 
 were placed over them preparatory to making our coffee — a most essen- 
 tial article with hard bread. 
 
 To one standing as a looker-on, the sight is amusing. For instance, 
 in one group, are some twenty tired and hungry fellows bending over 
 their cups, each intent upon the boiling of his own — but thump goes 
 somebody's foot against a rail, and on that rail are a score of precious 
 cups of coffee — over they go ; look, now, at the faces of the coffee 
 tenders ; one controls himself, bites his lip, and keeps quiet, another 
 swears, and all feel very badly that their coffee is spilled ; but with a 
 fresh supply they try it again, and perhaps by 10 or 11 o'clock the cof- 
 fee is drank, the hard bread is eaten, and the blankets spread for a 
 night's repose upon the ground. 
 
 The camp-ground, to-night, presents a most beautiful appearance with 
 its hundreds of fires, and the thousands of living objects moving about 
 them. Truly, there are some pleasant things in the soldier's life, chief 
 among which is the rest and warmth afforded by the night's encamp- 
 ment. 
 
 Friday, Dec. 12. Our march to-day has been hard, to say the least. 
 We have travelled full twenty miles, and through twenty-one of those 
 peculiar mud-holes with water full six inches deep, and from one 
 to three rods wide. What purpose these water places serve in the ar- 
 rangement of North Carolina is more than I can tell ; just at this time 
 they answer very well to keep our feet in a shocking state— wet, wet ! 
 We stopped this noon in a field for dinner, but had hardly time to com- 
 mence eating, before we heard the unwelcome bugle-note warning us to 
 fall in With such rapidity were we marched from the field that we an- 
 ticipated a brush with the Rebels, soon, and our surmisings seemed to be 
 confirmed by the fact that prisoners were soon carried to our rear. One 
 item of considerable interest to us boys I must note. By the road-side 
 stood a Rebel in custody of one of our cavalry ; the latter sat upon his 
 horse, holding a pistol, loaded and full cocked, within a few feet of the 
 
8 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 prisoner's head ; his look seemed to say, " move, if you dare." Not a 
 hair did the Rebel move, but with a sullen revengeful look he glanced 
 at us, while our forces marched by him. 
 
 Saturday, Dec. 13. 8.30 a.m. We are seated just now upon the 
 frround, with knapsacks slung, and equipments on, all ready for a start. 
 We a'^ain anticipate a fight to-day ; I trust that whatever comes we 
 may be found all ready. 12 m. We are seated by the i-oadside not 
 many miles from Kinston, where it is quite certain we shall have a fight. 
 Our rear artillery is moving to the front ; we expect every minute to go 
 forward and give the Rebels battle. 12.45 p. m. Our forces are now 
 beino' drawn up in line of battle in a large open field. Our regiment is 
 second in line, supporting a battery. We are seated on the ground, — 
 fancy we see Rebel bayonets glistening in the woods — it proves to be 
 our cavalry ; the sun is very bright and warm. Another hour and some 
 of us may not be dwellers in this lower sphere ; whatever is before us, 
 may we do our duty. Night finds us still in the same field ; no Rebels 
 have yet been seen. Rumor says that Kinston is taken by our advance ; 
 an improbable story. 
 
 Sunday, Dec. 14. 8 a.m. All ready for a start; we wait the order 
 to move. 11 A.M. Again we wait by the roadside; heavy firing 
 is heard a short distance ahead ; a messenger has just passed post-haste 
 to the rear. 11.15 a.m. Ten Rebel prisoners just passed to the rear 
 in charge of some of our forces. 4 p. m. We are now seated quietly 
 in a large field, witnessing the performances of a battery. " We have 
 met the Rebels and they are ours " ; or, at least, about 500 of them are 
 — the rest have left for other quarters, perhaps not quite as warm as 
 they found these to be. Being posted in an advantageous position on 
 one side of an almost impenetrable swamp, and having full command of 
 the road over which they supposed our troops must march if we ad- 
 vanced, — they little dreamed that a few short hours would find them 
 making a backward movement. 
 
 The part played by us in the conflict was somewhat of the active mil- 
 itary style. First, we were drawn up in a field to support a battery ; 
 then we were ordered down the road. Being drawn up in another field, 
 we unslung our knapsacks and placed them in piles, leaving a man from 
 each company to guard them. Shells were bursting, and shot flying 
 quite rapidly about us, and wounded men being carried by us, indicating 
 that there was work for us not far distant. Our Colonel, taking his 
 place at the head of the_ Regiment, said, " Boys, I want you to march 
 straight through the woods in front, and keep a good line." We started, 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 9 
 
 and entering the woods found it a swamp of the worst kind ; despite of 
 all we could do, our legs would sink above the knees, and, at every step, 
 vines and brush of various kinds served to make our walk through it 
 anything but pleasant. But the Rebels were what we sought, and not 
 pleasant things, so on we pressed. The killed and wounded of the 45th, 
 who were ahead of us, were on every hand ; every minute we expected 
 to receive the Rebel fire, when many of us would have probably met 
 the same fate as those of the 45tli ; but a gallant charge of the noble 
 10th Connecticut had routed the enemy and left us in possession of the 
 field. As we marched out into the open field, a squad of prisoners filed 
 past us — a miserable, wretehed-looking set — and, if they are a specimen 
 of North Carolina troops, there will never any be taken for their beauty 
 — that's certain. 
 
 The Rebels, in their retreat, endeavored to burn the Kinston bridge 
 behind them, but were unsuccessful in the attempt. In due time we fol- 
 lowed them and entered triumphantly into the very prettj village of 
 Kinston. Both troops and citizens had left the place, only a few pro- 
 fessedly loyal ones remaining behind. Piles of cotton and corn were 
 burning in the street, they doubtless being determined that we should 
 have no part of their poor possessions. After shelling the woods for a 
 while our forces proceeded to encamp for the night ; arms were soon 
 'stacked, and fires built. We shall rest to-night better for having the 
 satisfaction that our forces have met and whipped the enemy. Not a 
 man flinched in that " dismal swamp," notwithstanding the difiiculties, 
 perils, and horrors around us, but each and all pressed bravely on, intent 
 upon the work before him. The loss on our side I cannot estimate ; the 
 10th Connecticut lost, it is said, 104 men in killed and wounded, from a 
 regiment of 350. 
 
 Tuesday, Dec. 16. We started early this morning, and marched rap- 
 idly forward till our arrival at a place called Whitehall, wliere we found 
 the Rebels in force, ready to give us battle. Our regiment was drawn 
 up beside a rail fence, on one bank of the river Neuse, while the Rebel 
 infantry occupied rifle-pits on the other bank. Here they bad a fine 
 chance to fire at us, while ours to return the compliment was small, save 
 when their heads popped up from their rifle pits. Bravely did our 
 boys face the rebel bullets, and bravely did they handle their guns, los- 
 ing no opportunity to make a good shot. After firing about twenty 
 rounds apiece, we were ordered back, and back we went. Our loss in 
 this engagement is estimated to have been ten killed and eighteen 
 wounded. There were many narrow escapes. F. P. Adams, of Co. G., 
 
10 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 received a spent ball in his right side, tearing open his overcoat and 
 making a slight bruise. F E. Lincoln, of the same company, was bad- 
 ly wounded in the knee while guarding a pile of knapsacks ; also, one 
 of Co. G.'s drummer boys, E. S. Fisher, a lad of about fifteen, one who 
 had begged the privilege of coming with us. His wound was also in 
 the knee, and when taken up his first inquiry was, " Shall I be sent 
 home ? Can't I stay with the regiment the nine months out ? " 
 
 The Rebels having fled before the fire of our artillery and infantry, 
 we formed our line, and again went "marching along," feeling that we 
 had helped to accomplish another good work ; and here our boys had a 
 good opportunity to display whatever valor they might possess, and the 
 manner in which they did it is understood to be highly satisfactory at 
 headquarters. 
 
 Wednesday, Dec. 17. We broke camp quite early this morning, and 
 w^ent rapidly forward. Had not travelled far when firing was heard 
 ahead, and it soon became evident that we were going to have another 
 brush with the Southern chivalry. Our artillery and some infantry 
 were already disputing the possession of a railroad bridge and a portion 
 of the track, to destroy which we are told was the main object of our 
 expedition. Our regiment, with others, was drawn up in a field as a re- 
 serve. Soon we heard the joyful sound, "The rebels are retreating" ;, 
 cheer after cheer rent the air ; and when one of Gen. Foster's aides 
 rode up to Gen. Stevenson, and gave him the order to march his brigade 
 to Newbern, we felt pretty sure that victory was ours. "With a ready 
 step we turned towards home, and marched rapidly along, in most excel- 
 lent spirits. Heavy firing in our rear seemed mysterious ; if the en- 
 emy had retreated and left us in possession of the field, what need of 
 further firing ? Doubts and fears would fill our minds, and when an 
 aide rode post haste to the head of our column, and turned it about, our 
 suspicions were fully confirmed. Night had now come upon us, and 
 with diffieuUy we marched over the bad roads ; but in an hour like this 
 all difficulties must be overcome, and nothing thought of but the action 
 and its result. We went back quickly over the road, and silently filed 
 into a piece of woods, and waited for furtlier orders. As near as I can 
 learn the facts of the case, the necessity of our returning was deemed 
 important, inasmuch as two regiments of rebel infantry had thought best 
 to make a charge upon Belger's Battery. Twice they tried it, and twice 
 were they driven back, their ranks pretty well thinned by heavy charges 
 of cannister. 
 
 Their defeat made certain, our force was again turned about, and 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 11 
 
 again started for Newbern. Our route lay through forests of pines, and 
 these, having been set on fire, presented a truly magnificent spectacle. 
 On every hand was fire, and as the flames ran up the tall trees and 
 leaped from branch to branch, eagerly devouring whatever came in their 
 way, strange thoughts would come across the mind, and one could almost 
 fancy he saw spirits from the other world wandering amidst the flames. 
 After much rapid marching over rough roads, we were drawn up for a 
 night's encampment. And now, with our work accomplished, we will 
 lay ourselves down to rest, trusting that Morpheus will put his arras 
 gently about us and impart unto us sound and refreshing sleep, so that 
 on the morrow we may go on our way rejoicing. 
 
 Tlnirsday, Dec. 18. Have made good progress in our homeward 
 march, to-day, — reached an old camping-ground, where we stop for the 
 night. 
 
 Friday, Dec. 19- Our march to-day led us by Kinston bridge, or the 
 ruins of it, (for our forces have burnt it), and over the battle ground of 
 Sunday. We had a hasty look as we passed, where we would have 
 liked hours in which to survey the place. As we passed down the river 
 road, (the one on which the Rebels expected us to advance), we saw 
 extensive rifle pits, and huge enbankments thrown up to protect their 
 artillery ; had we taken that route, which was the nearest, we should 
 have met with greater resistance and loss. But, thanks to Gen. Foster, 
 whose wisdom led us the other way, the old adage, " The longest way 
 round is the shortest way home," proved very true in our case. At noon 
 we halted in a pleasant field for two hours, and finally encamped for the 
 night. The ground to-night is very damp, which will serve very well to 
 reinforce the colds that most of us already have. The usual fires of 
 rails, and the usual boiling and drinking of coffee takes place, and we 
 lay our weary bodies down again to get relief from " tired Nature's 
 sweet restorer." 
 
 Saturday, Dec. 20. Back at last in good old Newbern. Started 
 quite early this morning, and have marched about thirty miles ; our 
 boys, most of them, seemed bound to get home to-night, so while other 
 regiments encamped outside of the city eight or ten miles, ours pressed 
 on and reached their barracks about 8.30 r. m., tired, hungry, and cold. 
 Some of us to-day had a fine opportunity of witnessing what is called 
 " snuff-dipping," as practised by the ladies of the South. We met a 
 team which had a decided arky appearance, containing two middle-aged 
 females — natives of this land of turpentine and resin. Pale and hag- 
 gard were their countenances, indicating about as much intellect and re- 
 
12 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 finement as the beast before them. In one hand each had a good sized 
 tin can containing yellow snufF, in the other was held a short stick, with 
 one end battered so that when wet and put in contact with the snuff it 
 would adhere to it. The team was stopped by enquiring and fun-loving 
 boys, and questions asked and answered. Ever and anon the battered 
 stick would dive into the tin box, and then, guided by the fair hand that 
 held it, proceed to do its work upon the pearly (!) teeth of the holder. 
 But time and patience would allow no further talk, and the last relic of 
 the flood moved on, bearing its precious burden, leaving us something 
 new to think of. 
 
 Our march is at last over, and to-night we occupy once moi'e our com- 
 fortable bunks. During the march, which is estimated to have been full 
 one hundred and fifty miles in extent, our boys have borne up bravely ; 
 through all the troubles and difficulties of the v/ay all have manifested 
 a desire to do the best they could. Coming back, as we do, without 
 some who started with us, it would be well to let the past impress us 
 more deeply than ever of the importance of having our houses in order 
 and our lamps trimmed and burning, so that when called to follow them, 
 whether from the battle field or from the fireside, " We go as those who 
 wrap the drapery of their couch about them and lie down to pleasant 
 dreams." Scribe. 
 
 ON GUARD. 
 
 (Written by the light of a eamp-fire after the battle of Newberii. No one but a soldier can fully 
 
 appreciate it.) 
 
 On rriiard to-night ; 'tis a lonely place, Of its pulses warm ; and the caskets lie 
 
 And for two long hours I must wearily As cold as the winter's starless sky. 
 
 pace 
 
 To and fro 'mid the tall old pines How sad the thought that another day 
 
 Fringed with moss and clinging vines. Will bring again the battle fray ; 
 
 And, ore the close of the moiTow's light, 
 
 Scarce smiles a star through the clouds I, too, may sleep like these to-night. 
 
 aloft, 
 
 And the ocean breeze is damp and soft Past midnight hour, and I long to hear 
 
 That fans my fevered cheek and brow, The step to the soldier's heart most dear, 
 
 While I think of home and its loved ones "A sound that banishes all his grief, 
 
 now. The welcome tread of the " next relief." 
 
 On guard to-night ; 'tis a lonely beat. Ah ! here they come, and now I can 
 And, with lieavy heart and weary feet, keep 
 
 Amid the gloom and the dark I "tread, My next four hours in the land of sleep. 
 
 For I'm watching o'er the imburicd dead. And dream of homo and the loved ones 
 
 there. 
 
 Ah ! yester mom, how lightly throbbed Who never may know a soldier's care. 
 Full many a heart that death has robbed Anon. 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 13 
 
 TIIANKSGIYING ADDRESS. 
 
 (Delivered at the table of Company A, by the late lamented Clerk of the Police Conrt 
 at East Cambridge, A. L. Butler, Esq. Mr. B. was killed at the battle of Whitehall.) 
 
 Mr. President, and Fellow Soldiers of Company A : 
 
 It is with a feeling of diffidence that I now address you. Knowing 
 that there were two Everetts in this Company — a name that in the old 
 Bay State is synonymous with eloquence and oratory — I was astonished 
 when asked to address you on this occasion ; but having been assured 
 that it was neither oratory nor eloquence that was expected, only a few 
 honest words, to be spoken on this most happy day, I could not feel that 
 it was my duty to decline. 
 
 Mr. President : this is Thanksgiving day ; a good old New Eng- 
 land day, first observed by our forefathers nearly two centuries and a 
 half ago, in the then infant colony of Plymouth, after a year of hard- 
 ships and trials, such as none of us have ever witnessed or expei'ienced. 
 If they, in the fullness of their hearts, could appoint and observe a day 
 of thanksgiving and praise to God, how much more should we, with our 
 many blessings, unite in keeping this hallowed day. 
 
 Most, if not all of us, are keeping this day in a manner different from 
 any that we have ever before observed. We used to go to our homes, 
 where we were born and reared, or gather at the house of some fond 
 brother or sister, there to unite in a family circle, to talk over the scenes 
 of our childhood, and relate the varied experiences of the past yt ar. 
 In the evening, the younger members of the family would assemble at 
 some re-union festival, or go to the much talked of Thanksgiving ball, 
 there to 
 
 " Dance all nijj;lit, till broad daylight, 
 
 And go home with the girls in the morning." 
 
 Roast turkeys and chickens, plum puddings and mince pies, are as much 
 a part of a New England Thanksgiving as the parish sermon, or the 
 gathering around the family fireside. 
 
 How pleasant are the memories of this day. With what eagerness in 
 onr childhood, we used to watch the preparations that were being made 
 to render it a happy day. How willingly we used to lend a iielping 
 hand, when, at any other time, the labor would have taxed our strength 
 and good-nature. When we had arrived at the age ot niunhood, and 
 
14 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 gone forth in the world to seek our fortune, Thanksgiving week was the 
 time appointed for our return to the home of our youth. 
 
 For nearly a century and a half after this day was first observed, the 
 Puritans refused to keep Christmas, a day that is now kept by all Chris- 
 tian people throughout the world. Their hatred of the Established 
 church of England, and of the Catholic church of Home, caused by the 
 persecutions they had endured, was so bitter, tbat anything that savored 
 of the old church was rejected by them as idolatrous and wicked. Even 
 the cross, that emblem of Christianity, was rejected by our Puri- 
 tan fathers. We, their children, have learned to be less intolerant and 
 bigoted ; and the supremacy of Christmas in our hearts is only success- 
 fully contested by Thanksgiving day. Let us, while becoming more lib- 
 eral towards the opinions and customs of others, be very careful that 
 we do not forget to practise any of the many virtues of our Puritan 
 fathers. It was their industry and stern integrity that gave to them 
 an imperishable name in history, and a character to New England 
 and her institutions such as no other people or country have ever 
 acquired. 
 
 What man among us, during our late march through a portion of this 
 State, could help contrasting the want of industry, prosperity, and intel- 
 ligence that he daily witnessed, with the neatness, thrift, and happiness 
 of a New England village. I do not know what others may think, but 
 I believe that much of the success and prosperity of New P^ngland of 
 to-day can be traced to the principles, habits, and institutions that our 
 forefathers practised and established. 
 
 Success is inscribed on the Yankee character ; and wliatever the Yan- 
 kees attempt to perform, that will they accomplish, be it tlie building of 
 a Dutch oven, or the suppression of a Southern rebellion ; it is a fore- 
 gone conclusion when the Yankee says it must be done. 
 
 We have had to-day the poultry and puddings, but the family friends, 
 where are they ? As I look around these tables, I almost feel like say- 
 ing they are here ; and, as a soldier, I do say it. Tes, they are here to- 
 day. A larger family than we have ever before met on such a day as 
 this, and composed of friends, many of whom we had never seen one 
 short year ago ; but as soldiers it is our family. We are now a family 
 of soldiers, with a name shorter than any we have previously boj-ne. but 
 long enough to distinguish us as members of the family called Co. A. 
 In our new family relations we have discarded many of the comforts 
 and customs of civil life, such as the comforts of home, the luxuries of 
 the table, the amusements of the theatre, concert and dance, the instruc- 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 15 
 
 tion of the lecture, and, what is of more importance than all these I have 
 mentioned, the refining influence of woman's society. 
 
 But the soldier can still bo a gentleman ; and I am happy to state, 
 what I firmly believe to be the truth, that Co. A has as large a number 
 of gentlemen connected with it, as any company in the Regiment. If 
 acts of kindness between man and man, an interest in the welfare of the 
 whole company, and a general good feeling among all the members, both 
 officers and privates, are evidences of the gentleman, what I have stated 
 is true. Let us continue to emulate the conduct of the perfect soldier 
 and gentleman, so that we may be an honor to the old Bay State, and the 
 recollection of our soldier life in future years shall be one of pleasure 
 and pride. 
 
 We miss the picnic parties and suppers that we used to have at Read- 
 ville, and the company of those who came to see our much admired dress- 
 parades, laden with the choicest fruits of the garden, and pastry from the 
 pantry, the recollection of which is sufficient to make our eyes sparkle 
 and our mouths water. But we eat with a keener relish and better ap- 
 petite the rations that the Government furnishes. To-day we have en- 
 joyed the products of an oven built by the sweat and toil of our own 
 hands, such as all the cooks of Readville never witnessed. 
 
 "We also miss the music that used to enliven that dullest of all a sol- 
 dier's duty — guard-mounting — and make each day seem shorter and pleas- 
 anter for its cheering strains. We now have the promise of a re"-imental 
 band. May the efforts now making to organize a b&amp;nd be crowned with 
 succe. s, and the men of the 41th soon march to the inspiring strains of 
 their own music. How the hearts of all would leap with joy were we 
 to hear the band strike up with the " Star Spangled Banner," " Yankee 
 Doodle," or " The Girl I left behind Me." 
 
 Sinc(3 leaving R(;adville, we have learned much of the soldier's life 
 which we had never before experienced ; we are now " Jack at all 
 trades." At meal times each man seems to be practising the scene of 
 Oliver Twist, in the parish poor-house, and "asks for more"; but our 
 Beadle has got used to the scene, so that his astonishment is only when 
 we fail to come the second time. Our cook has not yet learned to make 
 his soup after the poor-house receipt, but gets it so rich that it is the de- 
 light of Co. A, and the envy of all outsiders. 
 
 It is a daily occurrence to see men employed in performing police 
 duty, shovelling, sweeping streets, and other like menial labor, who. pre- 
 vious to their enlistment, had never known wliat it was to perform any 
 kind of work, or had been engaged only in the lighter kinds of toil. 
 
IG THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 Notwithstanding the many hardships and deprivations we have had to 
 endure, I am proud to be able to say that they have been endured with 
 less complaint on the part of the men than will be heard among an equal 
 number in civil life. Each man has seemed to take it as unavoidable, 
 and to bear it with equanimity. May we continue to exhibit a friendly 
 spirit of rivalry between each man and each company, so that when we 
 shall get our discharge the verdict may be that every man did his whole 
 duty. 
 
 We have for a captain a man whom we are all proud to serve and 
 obey. In our eyes he is a model soldier, and I have been told that he 
 is spoken of by officers higher in rank than himself, as the captain of the 
 Regiment. We all know that the welfare of this Company is his daily 
 care. May our efforts to fulfill his Avishes and obey his commands be 
 such as to amply reward him for his trouble. That he has the confi- 
 dence of this Company in his loyalty of purpose, and ability to command 
 them in whatever situation they may be placed, is a fact that is a credit 
 to himself and his men. To the advice and assistance of Capt. Richard- 
 son, backed by the cooperation of Col. Lee, and the labor of our own 
 men, we are indebted for the entertainment of to-day. 
 
 May next Thanksgiving day find us citizens of a country at peace 
 with itself and all the world. May the rebellion that is waging war 
 against the Federal government be speedily crushed, and the leaders in 
 this wicked attempt to overthrow a free government meet with the pun- 
 ishment their crimes deserve. There are many homes in New England, 
 where sorrow and mourning have come during the past year, that would 
 have been filled with peace and joy to-day but for this rebellion. Many 
 a seat is vacant to-day which would have been filled but for the thous- 
 ands now in the Federal army, called there by the necessities of the gov- 
 ernment and a sense of duty and patriotism to their country. May the 
 success of our arms during the coming months establish our government 
 on a basis firmer than it has ever rested upon, and start it on the road to 
 prosperity and fame such as never before was witnessed. To-day the 
 hearts of our relatives and friends will be sent out to us in the array, 
 and the response that will meet them on the way will be heartfelt and 
 full. 
 
 Mr. President, I have endeavored to be brief; but as this is the 
 first and only address I have been called upon to make, I trust you will 
 pardon me if I have taxed your patience. In conclusion, I will give as a 
 sentiment what I believe you will all heartily respond to : Tiianicsgiv- 
 iNG Day. 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 17 
 
 THANKSGIVING IN THE BARRACKS OF CO. D. 
 
 /Q\ UR Puritan forefathers ; — we honor their memory, and cherish the 
 \^ institutions they established. Thanksgiving for the soklier ; no 
 drum-beat, no di-ill — a day of rest. Is it not a blessing ? What though 
 he do not keep it with Puritanic reverence ? What though fasting be 
 exchanged for feasting, and mirth and music take the place of prayer 1 
 Who shall say there is not heartfelt gratitude and thankfulness in the 
 soldier's Thanksgiving ? There is gratitude for the day itself, with its 
 precious memories of the annual gathering around tlie old fireside ; 
 there is thankfulness for the good things which take the place of his 
 common, coarse fare. There is praise in his song of mirth, reverence 
 in the good old songs of home, and who shall say that prayer is not 
 wafted up to God on the deep-toned voices that join in the closing hymn 
 at night ? The strong feeling of earnest, manly hearts takers the place 
 of cold formality of church and creed. 
 
 Such, at least, was our Thanksgiving in Newbern barracks. Compa- 
 ny D, of the 44th, divided into parties and messes, each mess makinc 
 arrangements in the culinary department according to individual taste, 
 utterly regardless of Uncle Samuel's ration regulations. Judging from 
 the way roast turkeys, and other good things to match, disappeared from 
 the different tables, one would say the sanitary regulations shared the 
 same fiite. 
 
 In the evening, there was a Company gathering, with all tlie more union 
 for the day's separation. The entertainment consisted of sono-s, decla- 
 mations, select readings, toasts, and speeches ; the whole prepared on 
 short notice. The responses to toasts were almost entirely extempore, 
 only a few minutes' notice being given to those expected to speak. 
 
 To the first regular toast, — " Thanksgiving day : may New En&lt;»land's 
 sons put the rebellious vSouth in a spirit to recognize it annually," — Cor- 
 poral J. B. Gardner responded briefly. He spoke of the origin of 
 Thanksgiving, and the reason of its transmission to us. He recalled 
 home Thanksgivings, and contrasted them with this ; and looked forward 
 to the time when we might celebrate a Thanksgiving in our own homes 
 — one whose origin should be a declaration of peace in a free, united 
 and prosperous nation. 
 
 The second regular toast — " The loved ones at home " — wrs fittingly 
 responded to by E. Fitzgerald, Jr. He said: Thanksgiving comes home 
 2 
 
18 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 to every one of us, in all its New England naturalness. Despite our 
 necessitous life, our inner man has been brought to a sense of the full- 
 ness of past Thanksgivings. By to-day's special privileges, " govern- 
 ment pies " have vanished before turkeys and other dainties. Therefore 
 WQ feel able to imagine the comforts of the home table. The fat turkey, 
 with the well flavored " dressing," whose mysteries the Yankee matron 
 alone knows, and the steaming pudding staring at us with its big plum 
 eyes ; — how such imagining waters the mouth ! But, aside from sensu- 
 ous reminiscences of home, come thoughts of the loved ones themselves. 
 We know that the dear mother shed at least one hot tear as she sat down 
 to the ample dinner ; and the stern father — did he not falter a prayer 
 for the absent ? Sisters and brothers were stiller at the name of the 
 soldier-boy, and prayerfully wished him home again. Ah ! comrades, 
 duty done, and done well, we will go home. The loved ones, though far 
 off', still live snug to our hearts. The old household — God bless it ! 
 
 Third regular toast : " Our new Commander of the Army of the Po- 
 tomac, Mtij. Gen. A. E. Burnside. May the laurels won at Roanoke be 
 renewed at Richmond." The President said he had the pleasure of intro- 
 duciug an anomaly — A. C. {sea) Fish — who would respond. Said Fish 
 spouted somewhat as follows : The good things Thanksgiving usually 
 brings, expected to be enjoyed by the soldier only in imagination, have 
 come in reality ; and have been so well appreciated, that he who expects 
 a speech — clear thoughts in clear language — looks for an inconsistency 
 as great as a sea Hsh, forty miles fropi the sea. Somebody has said, 
 " Let us take heed of the things that surround us, for To-Day is a king 
 in disguise." We can only re-i*cho the thought, we cannot realize it. It 
 is hard, too, to take heed of what is passing around us. Great battles — 
 material for a volume of history — are forgotten in a day ; we look for 
 greater events in the future. Pledges of the people to sustain the Pres- 
 ident, success at the polls, and proclamations are as nothing compared 
 with that victory which ought to be ours, and which alone can let in 
 light. The war has been waged twenty months ; with all the power 
 and energy put forth by the North, rebellion still holds us at bay. What 
 the nation needs now is a Napoleonic genius, a General who can wield 
 the mighty power of a million of men in arms, who can concentrate and 
 crush. It was thought at one time we had found the man in Gen. Mc- 
 Clellan. But out of a chaos of inaction came only the words, " All 
 quiet on the Potomac." People said he was " slow, but sure " ; we are 
 only sure that he was slow. The disastrous Peninsular campaign placed 
 Gen. Pope in command. The motto then was, " Spades to the rear ; 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 19 
 
 look before, and not behind." AVlien he retired, the question, " Is Rich- 
 mond ours," was changed to " Is Washington safe ? " Again Gen. Mc- 
 Clellan was called back. Antietam followed ; a golden opportunity to 
 destroy the Rebel army was lost. Then followed the waiting and re-or- 
 ganizing policy, until the salvation of the country demanded a leader for 
 the Army of the Potomac. The hero of Newbern and Roanoke, Maj. 
 Gen. A. E. Burnside, is the man. He has the confidence of the Presi- 
 dent, and the people ; the army believe in him. He has our confidence, 
 and m.9y it be our privilege to aid him. Let us think of what we can 
 do, not of when we shall go home. "When Gen. Burnside routs the 
 Rebels at Richmond, may we have a part in cutting off and capturing 
 them on their retreat towards the Gulf. 
 
 Fourth regular toast : " The Otfioers of Company D." Charles H. 
 Demerritt responded. Had we our glasses filled, we should all, I think, 
 drink to that toast most heartily. AVe have too many times manifested 
 the regard and esteem which we entertain for our officers, for me to allude 
 to it to-night ; and that those feelings are I'eciprocated, we have had too 
 many evidences to doubt. The efficiency of any comi)any depends upon 
 the relations existing between officers and men ; that ours has been effi- 
 cient is proved by its recent promotion ; and this is due, not as our Cap- 
 tain has modestly said, to us alone, but also to his unceasing exertions. 
 Since our arrival in North Carolina, and more particularly during our 
 late expedition, he has shown that he intends to stand by his Company ; 
 and I know that I speak your sentiments, as well as my own, when I as- 
 sure him that we will stand by him. The military qualifications of our 
 First Lieutenant were too marked to escape the attention of the General 
 commanding, and he has been called to perform more important and re- 
 sponsible duties ; but, wherever he may go, whatever position he may fill, 
 he will carry with him the best wishes of Co. D. But if we have lost 
 the services of one able officer, we are fortunate in having another whom 
 we know can make his place good. Though at present disabled by 
 wounds received in our first fight, we hope he soon will be able to per- 
 form his accustomed duties. In conclusion, gentlemen, I propose three 
 cheers for our Officers and our Orderly. 
 
 The fifth regular toast — " Old Boston ; God bless her from hub to rim " 
 — was responded to by Corporal M. E. Boyd. The City of Boston ! 
 who among us does not feel a thrill of joy and pride at the mention of 
 our beloved and noble city, whei'c those live who are dearer to us than 
 all else, and where the greater part of us have spent our days from child- 
 hood up ? Her name stands forth glorious, and if it is in our power to 
 
20 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 do anything to cause it to shine forth still brighter, we pledge ourselves, 
 one and all, it shall be done. On this Thanksgiving evening our thoughts 
 leave us in our North Carolina home, aad carry us back to our dear ones 
 as they gather around the Thanksgiving board ; and we wonder whether 
 the empty seat at the table is noticed, and whether, surrounded as they 
 are by luxuries, they remember us who have gone forth to do battle for 
 them and our country ; and as our mothers and fathers, sisters and broth- 
 ers, gather to celebrate this ancient hoUday, their thoughts wander after 
 us, and they wonder where we are and what we are doing, and \»Uiether 
 in the excitement of war we have forgotten the tender memories which 
 this day should call forth. Our thoughts are for them, and theirs are 
 for us ; and when we go back at the end of our service, which I trust 
 and know will be an honorable one, " Old Boston " will give her sons a 
 Thanksgiving before which this will seem as nothing. 
 
 Corporal II. D. Stanwood responded to the sixth and last regular 
 toast : " Tiie girls we left behind us." The reading of this toast started 
 such an all-absorbing train of reflections in the mind of the reporter that 
 he is unable to give the speech. He only remembers that there was loud 
 applause, and a statement to the effect that somebody was greatly cheered 
 by the approving smile of a pretty girl as we were marching down State 
 Street, to take the boat for Dixie. He has a faint recollection, too, of 
 hearing some one say that the remembrance of " the girl he left behind 
 him " made him a better soldier. 
 
 The singing of " Old Hundred " by the company closed the exei'cises 
 of the evening. The occasion was one to be remembered by us ; we 
 were observing a New England holiday, and our thoughts were among 
 New England homes. Our brief experience here has taught us to be 
 thankful for those homes. We can but contrast there with here. There 
 those institutions are cherished which truly exalt a nation ; here only 
 that is clung to, which drags a people down to barbarism ; there education 
 is universal, it is a civilized and Christian land ; here ignorance is estab- 
 lished by law, civilization a myth, and Christianity a lie. We never 
 knew before with how great a blessing God has blessed New England, 
 and with how deep a curse He has cursed the South. Matheies. 
 
 THANKSGIVING- AS OBSERVED BY CO. G. 
 
 fHE order of Gen. Foster making Nov. 27th, (the day of the usual 
 Thanksgiving in the Old Bay State), a military holiday through- 
 out his department, and recommending its observance according to the 
 
time-honored customs of the good people of that State, met the cordial 
 approbation of every member of the 44th ; and the boys of Co. G, 
 wishing to celebrate in a proper manner a day having so many sacred 
 associations clustering around it, as well as to show proper respect to the 
 General commanding, made their arrangements accordingly. 
 
 It was not to be supposed that a dinner, (for that, of course, is the 
 principal item in a Thanksgiving programme), could be got up in this 
 part of the world, and in camp, too, with that decree of taste and ele- 
 gance that would be afforded in a more civilized part ; but Co. G deter- 
 mined upon having a dinner, and a dinner they had, an account of which 
 I will try to give. 
 
 A committee was early appointed to make all needful aiTangements, 
 and the Chairman, Private E. G. Scudder, entered upon the duties 
 assigned him in an energetic and praiseworthy manner, ably supported 
 by his assistants, Privates John Kent and Charles Holland, and the re- 
 sult of their labors was in every way satisfactory to the boys. The 
 day was everything that could be desired, a fine warm sun shedding its 
 bright beams both upon the home circles, and upon us, far removed from 
 the dear ones in them. The air was mild, to a degree that prompted us 
 at first to set our long table out doors, but better counsels prevailed, and 
 it was arranged inside. Long boards extending the entire length of the 
 barracks, strongly supported by barrels, made a most excellent- table, af- 
 fording room for all our boys ; the seats made for the occasion were 
 rough and uncouth, but served the purpose. Rubber blankets spread 
 upon the table made superior table cloths, and smooth boards with raised 
 edges, made most excellent platters, upon which were placed the turkeys 
 and chickens, served up in true New England style. Mess-pans of apple 
 and cranberry sauce, sweet potatoes and onions, filled up the spaces be- 
 tween the former articles. 
 
 Nor must the ornamental work above and around be forgotten, for the 
 taste displayed and the effect produced was truly surprising, considering 
 circumstances. On either side, on a line with the upper bunks, were 
 hung woollen blankets, while guns, with fixed bayonets, were placed in 
 rows over them. At one end was suspended a drum, crossed with two 
 guns, with the Company flag immediately beneath ; at the other was 
 hung a knapsack, arranged in the same manner. Over the sergeants' 
 room were two swords crossed, with a red sash looped upon them. The 
 whole work, when complete, received the admiration of all. 
 
 When all was ready, the Company entered and took their seats, and 
 soon after our officers, who had been invited to dine with us, entered, 
 whereupon the Company rose and gave them three hearty cheers. Or- 
 
22 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 der being restored, Capt. Hunt read Gov. Andrew's proclamation, as be- 
 ing the most fitting opening to this festive occasion. This service ended, 
 we proceeded to make ourselves familiar with the rich feast before us. 
 Our first course consisted of oyster sauce passed around by our contraband 
 waiters ; then followed, in regular order, the other good things prepared 
 for the occasion. With remarkable rapidity did turkeys and chickens 
 disappear, each one of us considering himself bound to make way with 
 as large a quantity as possible. In due time the feast of good things was 
 ended, and then came " the feast of reason and flow of soul." Private 
 Jones, the toast-master for the occasion, upon being called upon, read the 
 following first regular toast : " The day we celebrate ; " which was re- 
 sponded to by Corporal Hobart. He thought, when asked to speak upon 
 this occasion, that it would be an easy task, and consented ; but the hour 
 had come, and he must say he felt too full for utterance ; this being consid- 
 ered a good thing, a laugh was had accordingly. Other remarks, eloquent 
 and pitiiy, were made by him, when he took his seat amidst loud cheers. 
 
 The next regular toast was then read : "Our country, right or wrong ; 
 we have enlisted ourselves for its vindication, and, with God's help, we 
 will accomplish what we have undertaken." Response by the entire 
 Company, by rising and singing " America." The next toast — " The 
 44th Regiment and its gallant commander ; may it never drift to the Lee- 
 ward, and may it often have a Dah at the rebels " — was responded to by 
 J. H. Elliott. The next was, " Co. G ; all present or accounted for." 
 Responded to by Lieut. J. C. White. He had good faith in Co. G, and 
 knew that in the hour of trial it would not be found wanting. A song, 
 " Viva la Co, G," by J. Dorr, followed the remarks of Lieut. White. 
 
 The next regular toast — " The Dinner ; the mind that conceived, the 
 hand that executed it are in every way worthy of it and of the occasion." 
 Response by Private E. G. Scuddor, Chairman of Committee of Ar- 
 rangements, who, in his usual happy style, gave us an account of his pro- 
 ceedings. " On being asked to act as your committee I hesitated about 
 engaging in ^o foul a proceeding. We were obliged to go on considera- 
 ble of a Chase to procure the necessary articles, and, of course, exerted 
 our Powers to the uttermost ; but we were finally able to get Holt of 
 some fine chickens which we found on board a schooner — they of course 
 coming from the Hatch — and you may be assured it relieved our minds, 
 for at one time we feared the only Bird we should be able to procure 
 would be a Jack Dorr, but after travelling to the Towns-end, fortune fav- 
 ored us, and the result is before you. If any one is disposed to find 
 fault with the dressing of the turkeys,, we would say in the most sage 
 manner that it is as savory as the time and place would permit. Our 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 23 
 
 Gardner was not able to furnish all we wanted. We hope you will all 
 rise in your seats aad pronounce the pudding " Plum Elegant." 
 
 The next regular toast, " Our Orderly Sergeant ; on land, or on sea, 
 no one can object to being kept under the Hatch," was responded to by 
 Orderly Hatch. He thought the boys had better be cautious about stand- 
 ing under the Hatch, as it was not yet warranted to stand. As he had 
 not yet received his warrant, this was considered a good joke, and brought 
 down the house. The next regular toast — " The left guide of Co. G ; 
 may he have an opportunity, next June, to take two points on the ground 
 on Boston Common." Loud calls were made for Sergeant Hastings, but 
 he had disappeared. The next toast was : " The girl I left behind me ; 
 in absence she makes a New-hall upon our affections." Responded to by 
 Sergeant Newhall in a happy manner. Then came, " Old Harvard ; its 
 learned walls have sent their ready few." Response by T. R. Harris. 
 The next was, " The Pioneer ; he axes himself, ' why did I enlist for a 
 military man ? ' " Responded to by J. H. Kent, chief Pioneer of Co. G. 
 Then followed a song entitled " Kingdom Coming," by S. A. Powers, re- 
 ceived with loud applause. The next regular toast — " Pay Day ; with 
 a jw.rse well filled, what care we how long it is delayed " — was responded 
 to by J. H. Pierce. The next : " The foreign element in our Company ; 
 their Lipps have often asserted that they Wood fight for their adopted 
 country." Responded to by L. M. Lipp, and loud calls were heard for 
 Charles Wood. The next toast was proposed by Orderly Hatch ; " Our 
 sweethearts and wives ; may the first be the last, and the last be the first." 
 Responded to by Lieut. Odiorne, who was received with great enthusiasm. 
 The next, proposed by C. J. McLitire, " Our INIothers." The next, and 
 last, by L. A. Chase — " Our friends at Home ; God bless them." 
 
 In consideration of the darkness that was now gathering about the 
 table, it was thought best to adjourn the meeting, which was accordingly 
 done, the Company joining in singing " Auld Lang Syne." Outside was 
 enjoyed a mock dress parade by the boys of Co. A. The evening hours 
 were spent quite pleasantly inside, declaiming, singing, &amp;c. Upon the 
 whole, Co. G congratulates itself upon the good time enjoyed, and only 
 regrets that their pleasure could not have been shared by at least some 
 of the loved ones at home. Scribe. 
 
 TIIiVNKSGIVIXa DAY IN CA^^ir. 
 
 T ITTLE did the kind friends at home imagine that the boys of Co. 
 Jy(^ E enjoyed so pleasant a Thanksgiving in Newbern as we did. One 
 
24 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 writes : " probably you are eating ' salt horse ' and ' hard tack,' or else 
 wading knee-deep the Southern swamps, on a toilsome march." If they 
 could have ridden out here in their carriages, as at '' old Readvillc," they 
 would have found the happiest set of fellows ever met. Everybody 
 pleasant except those unlucky ones who were put on guard ; of course 
 they received more than their share of pity, but no one seemed inclined 
 to take their places ! 
 
 The first amusement in order was a good game of foot-ball, with the 
 usual quantity of " rushing in," " fending out," shin-kicking," and bruis- 
 ing generally. In one rush after the ball a lieutenant and private rolled 
 over and over, together, in the dirt ; several officers joined with us, but 
 they did not stay long after the first game as the exercise was too violent. 
 
 Most of us had an idea that we were to have something extra nice for 
 dinner, which was the next important feature of the day ; but all were 
 surprised and over-joyed when filed to their seats at the table, which was 
 placed the length of the barracks, and covered with rubber blankets for 
 table cloths. Our shining tin plates and dippers made a very good show, 
 and the eftect was heightened by a large slice of soft bread (so called to 
 distinguish it from hard) leaning against every dipper. At intervals on 
 the board were large plates of golden butter, a treat to those poor fellows 
 who could not afford, or rather had no money to buy it. After some very 
 appropriate remarks by the Captain and Lieutenants, and six rousing 
 cheers for all hands, we sat down and commenced work upon the tui'keys 
 and chickens which were brought in nicely roasted, with a guard of mashed 
 sweet and Irish potatoes, rich gravy, and excellent cranberry sauce. 
 The carvers, who had been appointed beforehand, had some lively work 
 to perform, as the boys were hungry, and, of course, a little impatient. 
 However, affairs progressed finely, and soon nothing was heard but the 
 rattling of eating implements, and various expressions of delight, such as 
 the following; "Isn't this a jolly dinner?" "What tip-top sauce!" 
 " Give me some more turkey," etc. After the remnants of the turkeys 
 and chickens had been removed, five large plum-puddings, with hot sauce, 
 wei'e produced. We had forgotten all about " puddin' " and consequently 
 had eaten more of the first course than we otherwise should ; but we did 
 not hesitate long — not a moment. The attack was conducted in good 
 style, but our forces were some time in retreating. The boys settled 
 back a little from the table, (they could not lay back in their chairs as 
 tliey were accustomed to do at Parker's), to listen to the speaking, and at 
 the same time to partake of the dessert, which consisted of apples of 
 Northern growth, and raisins. I must not forget a joke which made 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 25 
 
 considerable fun ; it was perfectly characteristic of our second Lieuten- 
 ant. "While we were engaged with the pudding he rose and asked how 
 many there were who did not smoke ; a questioa he was desired to ask 
 by a gentleman in the Regiment procuring statistics. Several raised their 
 hands, when he very coolly remarked that he had a few cigars, but did 
 not know as he had enough for all ; the last part was drowned in the 
 cheers and shouts of the smokers, who fully realized their expectations of 
 a treat when the box was passed around. The usual amount of speech- 
 making followed, and with " Auld Lung Syne " we left the scene of fes- 
 tivity. 
 
 In the evening we gave a Dramatical and musical entertainment, the 
 programme of which was rather mixed, to be sure, but the best we could 
 offer, under the circumstances and considering the time we had to pre- 
 pare it. We made a very good stage, and with blankets and the Orderly's 
 sash, constructed quite a pretty curtain. The programme was as follows : 
 
 Song — Happy are we, to-night, Boys, o Ttr 
 
 Declamation — Entjland's Interference, .... F. S. Wheeler 
 
 Song— Oft in tlic Stilly Night, 
 
 Declamation— The Dyin&lt;,' Alchemist, S. G. Kawson 
 
 Readings— Selections, J- W. Cartwkight 
 
 Song — Viva 1' America, t tit- 
 
 Declamation— Spartacus to the Gladiators, . . . . -J- Watekman 
 Declamation — Beauties of the Law, also Bernardo del Cai-pio, . H. T. Reed 
 
 The Contraband's Visit, . . J. H. Myers and J. Bryant 
 Song — Gideon's Band 
 
 INTERMISSION. 
 
 Song — Rock me to Sleep, Mother ! 
 
 Declamation— Garibaldi's Entrance into Naples, . . G. H. VanVooruis 
 Song — There's Music in the Air tt -r t? 
 
 Imitations of Celebrated Actors, H. T. Reed 
 
 Declamation — Rienzi's Address to the Romans, . . . N. R. Twitphell 
 
 Old Folks' Concert, Father Kemv's Co. 
 
 Song — Home, Sweet Home, 
 
 in which the audience joined, as it was the closing piece. During the 
 performance the Colonel and Stati" OtBcers came in, and were very much 
 pleased with the exercises. By an order of the Colonel, " taps " did not 
 sound until ten o'clock, (it usually sounds at eight) ; but when it came 
 every light was extinguished, and the Barracks were as quiet as a mouse. 
 The day passed off so quietly, and yet so pleasantly, that the Colonel 
 expressed his pleasure in an order read at dress parade the following 
 day. So passed Thanksgiving Day with Co. E ; none of us will ever 
 forget it, and those of us who enjoy other Thanksgivings will look back 
 to this occasion as one of the bright spots in our life's pilgrimage. 
 
 E. A. R., of Cambridge. 
 
26 
 
 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 #ilit0 
 
 The Bay State Forty-Fourth. 
 YY^E trust that the dear ones at home, 
 ' ^ whose most earnest tlioughts are 
 connected with our Regiment, will 
 welcome this offering, not as a maga- 
 zine of articles carefully written and 
 revised, but in its true form, as the 
 hasty work of soldiers, prepared in 
 the interval of time between one ex- 
 pedition and another; the " one " re- 
 ferring to the late march upon Kins- 
 ton, Whitehall, and Everettsville, and 
 " another " to something which is yet 
 in the future — dim in our imagination, 
 uncertain as to form or place — but 
 still confidently expected. 
 
 Just a fortnight ago this Saturday 
 evening, that weary march of one 
 hundred and fifty miles was ended, 
 and the tired, foot-sore lx)ys of the 
 44th reached the barracks here. 
 Those of our civilian readers who 
 have journeyed until strength of body 
 and mind has left them, and, overcome 
 by fatigue, by the severest efforts 
 alone have reached, at last, their des- 
 tination, perhaps can appreciate, in a 
 measure, our feelings, when the bar- 
 racks, warmed and illuminated 
 through the thoughtful kindness of 
 a few who had remained behind, came 
 in sight, offering, to soldiers, the very 
 best shelter and accommodation. We 
 had broken camp, that morning, thirty 
 miles from Newbern ; but this en- 
 campment was the point to be reached 
 on Saturday night, — we were bent on 
 getting home ; and we venture to say 
 never was a sight of that dear spot 
 more welcome, than the drill and pa- 
 rade grounds of the 44th, dimly seen 
 by starlight, while from every window 
 of the barracks came a friendly 
 gleam. But what a charm was added, 
 when the letters from the one true 
 home, messages irom father, mother, 
 brother, sister, or dear friends, were 
 
 delivered by the handful ! that was 
 reaching home. Such was our last 
 experience. We have rested a fort- 
 night, we may remain quiet another 
 week, and still another, but it is very 
 doubtful. If marching orders come 
 before the ink is dry on the page be- 
 fore us, we are bound not to be sur- 
 prised, for our military experience 
 has hitherto been active, and action 
 we expect under our General. 
 
 If our friends fully appreciate the 
 circumstances that surround us, no 
 further apology, beyond the mention 
 of them is needed, when they open 
 the Bay State Forty-Fourth, and find 
 that we have disappointed them in 
 giving a noble title to a very simple 
 pamphlet ; but the name, for the love 
 we bear old Massachusetts, we cannot 
 change, even if, affected by Southern 
 atmosphere, the conductors of the 
 Magazine forget their former ability, 
 and spell, as well as punctuate, in the 
 style of some of the former inhabitants 
 of Newbern ; the latter part of which 
 we are led to write \^hen calling to 
 mind the inscription upon a wooden 
 tablet in " Cedar Grove Cemetery," a 
 picturesque old burial ground, but a 
 short distance from our camp. It 
 reads thus : 
 
 " Don't break the Shr- 
 uhery." 
 
 Soft ! a sudden recollection flashes up- 
 on our mind, which most forcibly sug- 
 gests that before charging upon Seces- 
 sionists the fault of being intolerably 
 illiterate, on account of the original 
 style of letter painting displayed in 
 the instance above given, we need to 
 be sure that no parallel example can 
 be found in the North. Our misgiv- 
 ings on the subject are, however, re- 
 lieved when we remember that Capt. 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 27 
 
 Winsor, the new Superintendent of 
 our own " Sweet Auburn," had the 
 larije board of regulations renovated 
 entirely, last spring, so that — 
 
 " No Smoling is allmved wh- (/) 
 He in the Grounds " — 
 
 after remaining some years, no longer 
 disgraces a beautiful spot. 
 
 Although separated from IMassachu- 
 setts friends, and deprived of the com- 
 forts of home and the social inter- 
 course with the loved circle, during 
 the long winter evenings that have 
 never before passed without some en- 
 joyment, we are determined to ask a 
 hearing in the manner we have chosen. 
 
 It is a fact well recognized by all 
 who attempt writing an article in 
 camp, that for some reason or other 
 ideas are stagnant, and literary work 
 is accompanied with great difficulty. 
 Still, without enumerating the hin- 
 drances that surround a soldier who at- 
 tempts to amuse you, we sul^mit the 
 inclosed to — our publishers, who will 
 put in clear type as much of the man- 
 uscrij)t as they can read, (we only 
 hope that the worst portion of the Ed- 
 itor's production is the most illegible), 
 and in time our friends will receive it. 
 Please pass no judgment upon the 
 Bay State Forty-Fourth, until we have 
 greater leisure, and better opportuni- 
 ties for making it the publication we 
 should wish it to be. 
 
 The following formg a part of a pa- 
 per read in Co. D, one evening ; it 
 was arranged at very short notice, but 
 its renewal in print will serve as a 
 pleasant reminder to the boys of that 
 Company of an evening in the bar- 
 racks. 
 
 The Hasty Puddinff. 
 
 What ready "stuff" circumstances 
 offered, we have rapidly mixed atid 
 moulded into a literary pudding — has- 
 ty, because picked up. and cooked in 
 fi hurry. Everybody loves pudding, 
 therefore everybody ought to be grate- 
 ful for a bit "of this. Circumstances 
 change things ; at home, we would be 
 discriminate^ preferring pure milk, 
 tvolden butter, and plums abundant 
 
 and sweet. Then the raeasurings, 
 and stirrings, and baking must be by 
 well-known hands. Here, what mat- 
 ter if the milk be scarce, and smack 
 of water? What if the butter be 
 semi-lanl, and the whole pudding made 
 up of good and bad, sweet and sour ? 
 The soldier, of all men, bends grace- 
 fully to necessity. Hence, if butter- 
 less" biscuit and ambiguous tea be all 
 he can get, he utters thanks and takes 
 them. He may grumble, but grum- 
 bling spices his gratitude. Kow, this, 
 the letter-pudding of our own concoc- 
 tion, though motley enough, we trust- 
 fully present to you. 
 
 Naturally stingy, the Hasty Pud- 
 ding is a spasm of liberality on our 
 part. Comrades and contributors, we 
 want you to eat. If, by the way, any 
 of you have helped us with scrapings 
 of your own labor, " fall in " promptly 
 for your share. Eat, come all, and 
 eat. Quinine is good, but the " Hasty 
 Pudding " is better. Friends, the sol- 
 dier needs no introduction to life. He 
 hates introductions. Why then, sin- 
 gularlv enough, should you wait for a 
 formal acquaintance with the " Hasty 
 Pudding " ? I thought you'd take it as 
 they tried to take Fredericksburg, by 
 storm. Come, sit down at table, and 
 eat. 
 
 Bivouac ! 
 
 " We are coming, Father Abraham, three hun- 
 dred thousand more," 
 
 imaginatively echoed along the dark 
 air, and the Northmen marched on in 
 silence, stern, with step weary, but 
 persistent. Mere figures they were, 
 their faces masked by night, their 
 voices hushed. The vague gloom had 
 made them lleshless shadows, hail there 
 not gone with them a solemn tramp, 
 and a continuous tinkling, as of cym- 
 bals, telling of mind and purpose. 
 No moon shone. Out from the dark 
 dwelling of the sky the many scattered 
 stars looked gravely down. Aloiig 
 their way, either side, stood the wil- 
 derness, gaunt, tangled, thorny, veno- 
 mous, hiiiing the hypocritic swamp, 
 toying with iniasmas. Silently toiled 
 these" armed thousands! Darkness, 
 and dreariness without — no cheer, no 
 
28 
 
 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 joy, no apparent promise — but God 
 within, God in their hearts. 
 
 Suddenly that bright gleam aheail, 
 at the end of the long forest-vista ! 
 Wliy does the host hasten at sight of 
 it ? " Camp-fires ! eamp-fires ! " sounds 
 along the lines ; the bentforms straight- 
 en, the deep sigh of weariness for the 
 moment ceases. Onward! onward! 
 the light widens and brightens ; a few 
 more persistent steps, and the forest is 
 ]ussed. What a scene ! glorious ! 
 On either side stretch immense fields 
 all aglow with a thousand fires ; massy 
 volumes of smoke roll sluggishly 
 through the air. Separate, in long 
 parallel lines, arc ranged wagons, can- 
 non, horses, men. Along the fires 
 group figures sitting, standing, crouch- 
 ing, indistinct in the dusky light. 
 And armed files are still pouring into 
 the fields, while on, on, up the road, 
 march the massive remnant, the blaz- 
 ing bivouac their guide and goal. 
 " Fall in for rails ! " and onward they 
 move — an army with rails. Camp is 
 reached ! tlie bivouac is complete ! 
 Sleep and rest are at hand. 
 
 Thus America plods forward in the 
 deep, dark night of rebellion, through 
 the wilderness of disaster. Thus, O ! 
 thus, may she meet many a bivouac 
 of cheer and rest ! 
 
 Mr. Horace P. Tuttle, the Astrono- 
 mer, has favored us with the following 
 list of the killed and wounded, and 
 also of those who had died in the 44th 
 llegiment previous to Jan. 17, 1863. 
 
 COMPANY A. 
 
 Killed— D. T. Newcomb, .1. W. Slocumb, 
 W. K. Meagher, A. L. liutler. 
 
 Wounded— Sergt. J. F. Clark, A. K. Tap- 
 pan, A. S. May, J. W. Greenwood, J. F. 
 Berry, W. Baniford. 
 
 COMPANY c. 
 
 Kliled-^Sergt. A. S. Courtis, Corp. E. H. 
 
 Curtis, A. F. Polio, C. E. Rollins. 
 Died — A. B. Moulton, fever. 
 
 COMPANY D. 
 
 Wounded — Charles Ewer — Frederic Jack- 
 son. 
 
 COMPANY E. 
 
 Killed — Charles Morso. 
 Wounded— C. H. Roberts. 
 
 COMPANY F. 
 
 Died — John C PoUitz, Josiah Moody. 
 
 COMPANY G. 
 
 Wounded— F. E. Lincoln, E. S. Fisher, 
 
 Drummer. 
 Died — H. G. Kimball, fever. 
 
 COMPANY H. 
 
 Wounded— Sergt. W. W.Howe, E. C. Cros- 
 by, R. V. De Peyster, H. Parker, E. A, 
 
 Jacobs. 
 
 COMPANY K. 
 
 Killed — G. E. Noyes. 
 
 The following is a list of the men 
 detailed from the 44th Kegiment for 
 various duties. We obtain a copy 
 of it through the kindness of Adjutant 
 Hinckley. 
 
 COMPANY A. 
 
 As one of Signal Corps, C. C. Mui-dock. 
 In Hospital Department, Private Miuin. 
 In Quartermaster's Dep't, A. L. Whipple. 
 
 COMPANY C. 
 
 In Hospital Department, N. W. Brooks. 
 At Brigade Headquarters, in Commissary 
 Department, W. C. Cotton. 
 
 COMPANY D. 
 
 As one of Signal Corps, G. H. Colby. 
 As Carpenter. J. F. Bacon. 
 As Painter, C. E. Wheelock. 
 
 COMPANY F. 
 
 As Draughtsmen at Headquarters, W. G. 
 Wlieelock, J. H. Curtis. 
 
 As one of Signal Corps, G. W. French. 
 
 As Baker, C. S. Moody. 
 
 As Clerk in Brigade Quartermaster's De- 
 partment, E. D. Hull. 
 
 As Wagoner, T. P. Holt. 
 
 As Commissary iu General Hospital, W. 
 H. Lathrop. 
 
 In Regimental Hospital, as Nurse, J. F. 
 Dean. 
 
 As Clerk to JIajor Stackpole, Judge Advo- 
 cate, J. E. Dean. 
 
 COMPANY G. 
 
 As one of Signal Corps, A. N. Elliott. 
 
 As Wagoner, A..B. Hart. 
 
 As Harness Maker, C. H. Cormier. 
 
 COMPANY H. 
 
 As Teamster, H. H. Belcher. 
 
 As Hospital Wagoner, A. H. Curry. 
 
 lu Hospital Department, W. A. SalTord, G. 
 
 A. Ives. 
 As Clerk at Headquarters, A. F. Bo one. 
 As Baker, T. L. Gibbs. 
 
 COMPANY I. 
 
 As Clerk to Lt. Goldtliwaite. L. Ehoades. 
 
 As Clerk to Dr. Breed, T. I'inkhani. 
 
 For duty to Lt. Goldtliwaite, B. F. Adams. 
 
 COMP.VNY K. 
 
 As Purveyor's Clerk, W. A. Gould. 
 
 Much important matter is crowded 
 out of this number. In our next we 
 shall give the remainder of the Roll, 
 1 some interesting memoirs, &amp;c. 
 
THE BAY STATE FOKTT-FOURTH. 
 
 29 
 
 ROLL or THE 44TII REGIMENT, M. V. M. 
 
 STAFF AND FIELD OFFICERS. 
 Colonel — FRANCIS L. LEE, of Newton. 
 
 Lieut. Colonel. 
 
 Ed-ward C. Carot, Brookline. 
 
 Major. 
 
 C. W. Dabnet, Jr., W. Eoxbiiiy. 
 
 Surfjeon. 
 
 Robert Ware, Boston. 
 
 Assist. Sunj. 
 
 T. W. Fisher, Medwaj. 
 
 Qitortennaster. 
 
 Francis Bush, Jr., Boston. 
 
 Adjutant. 
 
 W. Hinckley, Lowell. 
 
 Chaplain, 
 
 Edward H. Hall, Plymouth. 
 
 Sen/eant Major. 
 
 W. 11. Bird, Koxbury. 
 
 Quartermaster Sergeant. 
 
 F. S. GiFFOKD, New Bedford. 
 
 Commissai-y Seiyeant. 
 
 C. D. WooDisriiY, Boston. 
 
 Hospital Steward. 
 
 W. C. Brigham, Now Bedford. 
 
 Pi-incipal Musician. 
 
 George L. Babcock, New Bedford. 
 
 Captain — 
 1st. Lieut. — Jared Coffin, 
 
 Privates. 
 At wood, J. M., Well fleet 
 Bailey, C. H., Boston 
 Bamford \V., N. Andover 
 Bass, J. A., Boston 
 Bellows, H. H., Holliston 
 Berry, J. F., Boston 
 Bickinore, A. S., Cambridge 
 Bloom, J. N., Boston 
 Brown, F. T., Maiden 
 Brown, W. W., Saugus 
 Butler, A. L., Cambridge 
 Clark, J. F., W. Cambridge 
 Cole, R. S., Boston 
 Conaiit, J. H., Brighton 
 Cragin, G. N., Boston 
 Creelman, E. T., N. Andover 
 Cuthbert, .J., N. Andover 
 Derby, W. H., N. Chelsea 
 Dodniun, N. if., Needham 
 Edmands, A. \V., Cambridge 
 Everett, A. H., ' " 
 Everett, G. E., Canton 
 Fielding, G. \V., N. Andover 
 Flanders, N. C, " 
 
 Fuller, A., Needham 
 Fuller, E. N., •' 
 Gibbs, F. F., Waltham 
 Gibson, VV., N. Chelsea 
 Gott, J. E., P.oston 
 Gould, A. F., Lexington 
 Grav, W. A., Dorchester 
 Green, W. H., W. Cambridge 
 
 COMPANY A. 
 
 J. M. RICHARDSON, Hubbardston. 
 
 Boston. I 2nd. Lieut. — C. G. Kendall, Boston. 
 
 Greenwood, J. W., Needham 
 Grover, C. A., Lexington 
 Hammond, .J. K., Cambridge 
 Hanson, F. B., Boston 
 Hartwell, A. H., Waltham 
 Hartwell, II. W., " 
 Hill, E. L., Boston 
 Howard, M., N. Andover 
 Hunting, 1., Jr., Needham 
 Hutchinson, G. S., Boston 
 Hubbard, 11., .Jr., Boston 
 Ingrahani, 11., Framingham 
 Johnson, A. S., Needham 
 Killian, J. H., 'Truro 
 Knox, S. H., Dorchester 
 Lee, Eugene C, Boston 
 Lovejoy, G. W., Andover 
 Lyon, E., Needham 
 Lyon, IL, " 
 ilatui, J. H., Cambridge 
 May, A. S., Needham 
 Meagher, M. H., Boston 
 Melville, H. F., P.righton 
 Montgomery, F. D., Boston 
 Jlooney, W. II., Cambridge 
 Moseley, W., Needham 
 Murdock. C. C, Wareham 
 Newcoinb, D. T., Medford 
 Noyes, J. C, Boston 
 Noyes, J. L., W. Cambridge 
 Pierce, W. IL, N. Chelsea 
 Rand, E. R., Boston 
 Rogers, L. W., N. Andover [ 
 
 Russell, H. Jr., Maiden 
 Russell, J. W., W Cambridge 
 Sargent, J. T. Jr., Boston 
 Schayer, E. A., Roxbury 
 Shackford, S. T., Boston 
 JSiocum, J. W.. Holliston 
 Smith, D. D., Weilflcet 
 Spring, W. S., Jr, Dorchester 
 Steele, C. L., Boston 
 Tappiin, A. K., Boston 
 Taylor, J. P., Tewksburv 
 Teel, W. F., W. Cambridge 
 Thomas, J. C. C, Beverly 
 Thompson, V. D., Dorchester 
 Tobey, T. F., Wareham 
 Trott, G. F., Boston 
 Tukey, J. E., W. Cambridge 
 Upton, L. E., Cambridge 
 Wall, C. J., Koxbury 
 Wallace, J. A., Maiden 
 Wellington, J. M., Waltham 
 Wellington, G. F. S., " 
 Wellinutoii, W. S., " 
 Whcaton, J. W., Roxbury 
 Whipple, A. L., Hamilton 
 Whipple, S. A. F., " 
 Whitnnirsli, J. G., Needham 
 Whittier, H. C, Boston 
 Wiley, D. W., Wellfleet 
 Wilkins, J. G., Watertown 
 NVood, C. P., Holliston 
 Yendoll, C. A. Jr., Boston 
 
 * Wo could obtain the names of the Corporals and Sergeants of only one Company, 
 as they are not on the Rolls at the State House. 
 
30 THE 
 
 BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 
 COMPANY B. 
 
 
 Captain — J. M. GRISWOLD, Newton. | 
 
 \st. Lieut. — F. H. Forbes, 
 
 Newton. | 2nd. Lieut. — J. A. Kbnrick, Newton. | 
 
 Privates. 
 
 Farnum, E. H., Newton 
 
 NeAvell, C, Needham 
 
 Abbott, C. F., Newton 
 
 Eaves, A. J., " 
 
 Patten, C. C, Newton 
 
 Almon, D., " 
 
 Felt, J., " 
 
 Penderghast, J., " 
 
 Baker, T. E., 
 
 Fields, C. S., " 
 
 Potter, A. F., " 
 
 Bamberg, T. B., " 
 
 Gardner, S., " 
 
 Reed, H. F., 
 
 Barrows, J. S., " 
 
 Gillespie, W., " 
 
 Richardson, W. H., " 
 
 Bassforci, E. P., " 
 
 Gleason, M., " 
 
 Robinson, W. W., " 
 
 Batchelder, S. G. A., " 
 
 Gray, E., " 
 
 Rogers, \V. M., " 
 
 Beck, J. H., Boston 
 
 Hamblin, J. C, " 
 
 Salsburv, B. G., " 
 
 Belcher, C. A., Newton 
 
 Harding, N. F., " 
 
 Sedwick, J. H., " 
 
 Belcher, W. H., " 
 
 Harris, Arland, " 
 
 Smallwood, J. B., " 
 
 Billings, J. E., " 
 
 Hawkes, J. Q. A., " 
 
 Snipe, S. T., " 
 
 Brady, J. W., 
 
 Hazelton, F. J., " 
 
 Surplus, Chas, " 
 
 Breimin, John, Needham 
 
 Hazelton, S., " 
 
 Sweeney, W. J., " 
 
 Brooks, C. B., Newton 
 
 Hill, George N., '' 
 
 Sylvester, J. W. •' 
 
 Brooks, G. W., " 
 
 Holmes, J. R., " 
 
 Teague, F. W., " 
 
 Buck, E. R., " 
 
 Hopkins, B., " 
 
 Tilton, D. P., " 
 
 Carlton, J., " 
 
 Hunting, F. H., " 
 
 Towle, J. E., " 
 
 Clapp, D. C, Boston 
 
 Hyde, H. N., Jr., " 
 
 Trowbridge, W. 0., " 
 Tufts, F. W., N. Chelsea 
 
 Clarke, E. H., Newton 
 
 Jenkins, J., " 
 
 Coffin, J. C, " 
 
 Jordan, W. E., " 
 
 Tufts, N. W. W., Newton 
 
 Coleman, P., " 
 
 Keyes, G. L., " 
 
 Walker, S. A., 
 
 Corey, T. F., Brighton 
 Crane, Z. A., Newton 
 
 Knight, C. W., « 
 
 Washburn, J. A., " 
 
 Lamson, G. W., " 
 
 Welch, T., 
 
 Dalton, P., " 
 
 Lucas, R. M., " 
 
 Wetherhee, G. E., " 
 
 Derby, J. P., 
 
 :Mansfield, A. H., " 
 
 Wetherell, H. B., « 
 
 Desmond, A., Ware 
 Dresser, S. H., Newton 
 
 Mansfield, T. F., " 
 
 White, S. H., Quincy 
 
 McSherrv, B., " 
 
 Whitney, C. E., Newton 
 
 Dresser, S. M., " 
 
 Mero, John B., " 
 
 Wilson, C. H., " 
 
 Duncan, J. E., " 
 
 Mitchell, E. F., 
 
 Withington, J. S., " 
 
 Edmamls, T. S., Newton 
 
 Milliken, E. W., " 
 
 Wetherell, H. B., » 
 
 Erhart, J. G., 
 
 MuUin, W. T., " 
 
 York, W. F., 
 
 Everett, VV. P., " 
 
 Nagel, R., " 
 COMPANY C. 
 
 
 Capta 
 
 IN — J. H. LOMBARD, 
 
 Boston. 
 
 \st. Lieut. — G. B. Lombar 
 
 D, Boston. 1 2nd. LieiU. — J 
 
 r. W. Briggs, Boston. 
 
 Sergeants. 
 
 Alley, C. M., Lynn 
 AUine, W. H., Boston 
 
 Danforth, G. W., W. C'mb'e 
 
 Cunningham, C. A., Boston 
 
 Drew, Arthur, Boston 
 
 Fitz, Frank, Pirookline 
 
 Ames, D. E., " 
 
 Everett, G. H., Wrcutham 
 
 Hed^e, W., Plymouth 
 Pond, A. C, Boston 
 
 Barden, F. S., Marion 
 
 Fogg, F. W., Boston 
 
 Bean, H. S., Boston 
 
 Gibbs, T. 0. S., Cohasset 
 
 ' Tyler, P. S., " 
 
 Bolles, J. T., Cambridge 
 
 Glazier, F. B., Garchier 
 
 
 I'.oynton, T. S., Framingham 
 
 Hadley, S. B., Boston 
 
 Corporals. 
 
 Bradbury, W. S., Cambridge 
 
 Hadley, AV. F., W. Camb'dge 
 
 Barker, C. E., Boston 
 
 Bradlee,"j. E., Boston 
 
 Hall, R. M., Dorchester 
 
 Courtis, A. S., E. Cambridge 
 
 Bradt, C. A., Lowell 
 
 Hawley, J. F.. Boston 
 Hawlev, W. H , " 
 
 Curtis, E. H., Boston 
 
 Bradt, F. 0., " 
 
 Cutting, A., " 
 
 Bruerton, J., Boston 
 
 Hill, H. K., W. Cambridge 
 
 Durrage, E. C, " 
 
 Bryant, A. S., " 
 
 Hiscock, C. H., Cambridge 
 
 Lawrence, C. C., " 
 
 Brooks, N. W., Dorchester 
 
 Holmes, T., Lynn 
 
 Page, W. C, 
 
 Carpenter, A. F., Boston 
 
 Horton, A. T., Boston 
 
 Smith, F. W. Jr., " 
 
 Coolev, P. L, " 
 
 Hovey, J. L., 
 
 
 Coolidge, G. T., " 
 
 Jones, L, S. Boston 
 
 Privates. 
 
 Cotton, W. C, " 
 
 Jones, S. A., " 
 
 Adams, G. H., Brookliue 
 
 Cutler, F. E., " 
 
 Kettell, G. B., Roxbury 
 
THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 31 
 
 Malionev, E. F., Boston 
 Mellen/M. Jr., " 
 Merrill, 0. S., N. Andover 
 Morse, G. J., Boston 
 Mum-oe, T., " 
 Murray, J. H., Cambridge 
 Newell, H. J., Boston 
 Norris, J. M , " 
 Osborn, C. H., " 
 Patten, J. M., W. Cambridge 
 Peaks, J. D., Cambridgeport 
 Pierce, A. P., Dorchester 
 Plummer, C. S., Boston 
 Polio, A. F., " 
 
 Polio, J. B., " 
 
 Pope, Richard, S. Boston 
 Preston, G. 0., Boston 
 Proctor, G., " 
 
 Randall, \V., Cohasset 
 Ray, G. H., Boston 
 Pea, J. P., 
 
 Richardson, F. W., Gardner 
 Pichmond, W. T., Boston 
 Roljiiison, .1. H., Camb'gep't 
 Robinson, R. T., " 
 
 Rogers, G. R., Boston 
 Rollins, C. E., Brookline 
 Rollins, G. M., " 
 Sackrider, G. M., " 
 Smith, J. R., Exeter, N. H. 
 
 Small, J. W., Boston [bridge 
 Smallidge, W. A., K. Cam- 
 Stearns, I. R., Chelsea 
 Temple, H. W., Boston 
 Thomas, D. J.. " 
 Trescott, E. AV., Roxbnry 
 Vinson, S. \V., Dorchester 
 Walker, E. C, Brookline 
 Ware, VV'., Milton 
 Warren, W. H., Brookline 
 Wentworth, P. H. Jr. Roxb'y 
 Whitcomb, C. D., Boston 
 Whittemore, C. H., Hopkiu- 
 Wilmot, H., Boston [ton 
 Willard, E. A., Cambridgep't 
 
 COMPANY D 
 
 Captain — H. D. SULLIVAN, 
 1st. Lieut. — James H. Blake, Boston. | 2nd. Lieut. — 
 
 Privates. 
 Adams, C, Medtbrd 
 Allen, 0., Boston 
 15acon, J. F., " 
 Bacon, S. A., Harvard 
 Bancroft, G. F., Groton 
 Barker, G. G., Bedford 
 Bates, D. D., Northfield 
 Bartlett, S. S., Plymouth 
 Beal, C. W., Boston 
 Beal, G. W., Quincy 
 Blanchard, A. Jr., Hingham 
 Blanchard,.J. A. W C'mb'ge 
 Boyd, M. E., Boston 
 Brewster, J. B., Plymouth 
 Burchstead, B. F., Boston 
 Burchstead, J. H., " 
 Butler, H., Groton 
 Carter, G. H., Boston 
 Chickering, C. C, " 
 Child, F. D., 
 Colbv, G. H., " 
 
 Crane, E. W., " 
 
 Crane, W. D., " 
 
 Currier, C. E., Cambridgep't 
 Currier, G. C, " 
 
 Demerritt, C. H., Boston 
 Ells, N. I., " 
 
 Ewer, C. C, 
 
 Fish, A. C, .lonesville. Wis. 
 Fitzgerald, E., Jr., Portsm'h 
 Flanders, F. M., E. C'mb'ge 
 Flanders, J. C, Lyuu 
 
 Flanders, W. H., Boston 
 Gardner, J. B., Roxbury 
 Gibbs, W. E., W. Cambridge 
 Gillev, S. M., Boston 
 GoflVW. C, " 
 
 Haines, Z. T., Strong, Me. 
 Hemmenwav, A. A., Fr'h'm 
 Hight, G. W., E. Boston 
 Hobart, G. ii., W. Newton 
 lloev, W. I., Cambridge 
 Holbrook, A. P., " 
 Hosmer, E. B., Harvard 
 Howard, D., Boston 
 Howard, H., " 
 
 Howard, W., " 
 Ireland, W. C, " 
 Jackson, F., " 
 
 Jacobs, A., S. Scituate 
 Jones, W., Hingham 
 Keinieson, L., " 
 Knight, D. T., Boston 
 Lane, C. C, Waltham 
 Leighton, J. E., E. Cambr'ge 
 Leatherbee, W. B., Boston 
 Litchfield, J. H.. Jr., H'gh'm 
 Littlefield, H. W., Jlilton 
 JIann, H. ^M., Boston 
 
 Messinger E. A., " 
 Millar, W. K., Waltham 
 Moody, W. I., Boston 
 Neal,'W. H., " 
 Newell, C. D., Framingham 
 Nevvhail, F. A., Southboro' 
 
 Boston. 
 
 Asa H. STEBiiiNs, Boston 
 
 Nourse, H., Bedford 
 Page, T., Boston 
 Paine, J., " 
 Parsons, W., Cambridge 
 Pear, T., Cambridgeport 
 Pierce, W. W., Maiden 
 Reed, C. E., Boston 
 Reed, J A., Hingham 
 Reed, W. G., Boston 
 Savery, W. E., \Veymouth 
 Sawiii, G. W., Boston 
 Sayer, F. A., " 
 Siiifionds, J. W., Jlelrose 
 Spencer, C. H., Camb'gep't 
 Stanwood, H. D., Boston 
 Stephenson, E. T. C. H'g'hm 
 Stephenson, W. L., 
 Stevens, H. P., S. Scituate 
 Sturtevant, C. W., Roxbury 
 Taylor, J. H., Boston 
 Treat, W. P., Canton 
 Tripp, G. L., Boston 
 Tonrtcliot, E. P., Charlest'n 
 Tucker, E., Maiden 
 Tuttle, H. P., Cambridge 
 Vose, C. H., S. Scituate 
 Wade, J. K., Boston 
 Ward, C. F., " 
 Waterman, J. H., Jr., R'xb'y 
 \\ aterman, R. C' S. Scituate 
 Wetiierell, J. W. Jr., Boston 
 Wheeler, C. E., Cambridge 
 Wheeler, F. D., " 
 
 COMPANY E . 
 
 Captain — S. W. RICHARDSON, Boston. 
 1st. LietU.—J. S. Newkll, Boston. | 2;m/. Lieut.— J. S. Cumstox, Boston. 
 
 Baldwin, F., Waltham Bryant, ,1., Boston 
 
 Bedell, C. H., lioston Briidish, A. H., " 
 
 Blanchard, K. R., Waltham Mutrick, G. E. Jamnicft Pl'ns 
 
 Blanchard, W . L., " Cartwright, J. W., Boston 
 
 ISowman, F. F., Boston Cheney, J. H., " 
 
 Primtes. 
 Adams, G. H., Cambridge 
 Adams, .W. R., " 
 Allen, W. A., 
 Barnes, T. L., Waltham 
 
32 
 
 THE BAY STATE FORTY-FOURTH. 
 
 Clough, S. A., Boston 
 Cross, II. C, Siiiigus 
 Currier, G. G., IJo.ston 
 Dean, W., Waltlinm 
 l)y.;r, G. L., Boston 
 Emerson, W. F., Waltham 
 Fillebrown, G. E., " 
 Flagg, J. P. Jr., Cambridge 
 Fletcher, W. .J. Jr., " 
 Hastings, F. J., Cambridge 
 Haves, \V. !•'., I'&gt;oston 
 Hight, H. 0., Cambridge 
 Holmes, S. A., Uoston 
 Homer, H. A., Cambridge 
 Johnson, H. W., iioston 
 Jones, P. F., Koxbury 
 Joy, C. F., 15riglilon 
 Kendall, A. H.^ Waltham 
 Kent, F. A., Boston 
 Learned, F. S., Watertown 
 Lewis, J. B., Jr., Heading 
 Livermore, W. B., Waltham 
 Loheed, T., Boston 
 
 Loring, A. B., Jr., " 
 Lovejov, J. W., Cambridge 
 Magouii, F. D., " 
 
 Mann, L G., Boston 
 MasoiJ, T. L)., " 
 
 Merrill, A. F., Boston. 
 Miller, L., Waltham 
 Moore, E. \'., Boston 
 Moore, J. F., Waltham 
 Morse, A. L., Mdton 
 Morse, C!., Bostcjn 
 Myers, J. H., Chelsea 
 I'age, A. K., Boston 
 Park, C. S., Groton 
 I'ursons, M. A., Charlest'wn 
 I'atten, T. H., Watertown 
 Pearce, \. H., Boston 
 i'eirce, H. T., Watertown 
 Pettingill, E. M., Boston 
 Piper, G. F., Cambridge 
 Plimpton, M. V., Uoston 
 Pope, G. 15., Waltham 
 Pond, B. F., Belmont 
 Price, F. J., Jr., Cambridge 
 Pulsifer, G. L., Boston 
 Ramsey, K. A., Cambridge 
 Rawson, S. G., Boston 
 Reed, H. T., Chelsea 
 Rice, J. B , .Tr., Cambridge 
 Richardson, E., " 
 
 Roberts, C. H., Melrose 
 Robbins, J. A. Watertown 
 Kussell, G., Boston 
 
 Sampson, W. P.., Boston. 
 Sawyer, W. F., .Maiden 
 Sherman, J. M., Waltham 
 Smith, E. P., " 
 
 Smith, G., Boston 
 Stevens, E. L., Brighton 
 Sutton, C. C, Boston 
 Tackney, J., '' 
 Thayer, A. F., Newton 
 Tower, H. C, \\ altham 
 Trott, S. P., Boston 
 Tucker, C. E., Boston 
 Twitchell, N. R., " 
 Tyler, C, Cambridge 
 Van Voorhis, G. H., Maiden 
 Wallace, E. A., Winchester 
 Ward, W. F., Cambridge 
 Warren, J. B., Boston 
 Whall, C. H., " [bury 
 Wheelwright, G. W. Jr. Rox- 
 White, E. P., Milton 
 Whitney, W. L. Jr., C'mb'ge 
 Walcott, G. P., Boston 
 Wilder, V. A., Roxburv 
 Wilder, W. S., Boston' 
 Worth ly, J. C., " 
 Wj-eth, J. J., Cambridge 
 
 COMPANY F. 
 
 Captain — CHARLES STORROW, Boston. 
 \st. Lieut. — A. S. Hartwell, Natick. | 2»rf Lieut. — T. E. Taylor, Newton. 
 
 Privates. 
 Ashenden, R, E., Boston 
 Ashley, .T. E., Charlestown 
 Atkins, F. H., Cambridge 
 Badger, W. Jr., N. Chelsea 
 Balch, F. W., Boston 
 Barnard, F. H., " 
 Bartlett, E. J., Concord 
 Brown, W. H., Boston 
 Capen, J. H., '' 
 Clapp, H. A., Dorchester 
 Clark, H. A., S. Hadley 
 Cobb, C, Boston 
 Cobb, D., " 
 
 Coburn, H. B., " 
 Coggswell, E. R., Cambridge 
 Colburn, L, Dover 
 Cook, C. E., Chelsea 
 Cook, J. F., 
 
 Copeland, W. E., Roxburv 
 Curtis, J. H., Waltham 
 Davis, W., Charlestown 
 Dean, J. E., lioston 
 Dean, J. F., Cambridge 
 Denny, A. W., Roxbury 
 Devens, F. W., " 
 Dodge, A. L., Jjoston 
 Dodge, F. L., " 
 Fox, C. W., Cambridge, 
 Francis, C, Lowell 
 French, G. W., Boston 
 Fuller, B. G., " 
 Gay, E. F., Dover 
 
 Gibbs, J. M., Waltham 
 Goldthwait, C. W., Boston 
 Goldthwait, G. F., " 
 Goodwin, F., " 
 
 Hanson, J. ii., " 
 
 Hayward, J. W., Roxbury 
 Hewins, E. K., Boston 
 Hevwood, W. T., Boston 
 Higgins, .1. W., 
 Holbrook, S. L., Dorchester 
 Holt, T. P., Cambridge 
 Hopkinson, F. C, " 
 Howe, E. H., " 
 
 Hovt, H. M., Boston 
 Hull, E. D., Roxbury 
 Hunnewell, (i. A., Boston 
 Ligrahara, N. H., S. Hadley 
 Ingraham, W. F., " 
 James, G. W., Ccneord 
 Johnson, A. P., Cambridge 
 Jones, E. L., Boston 
 .Jones, G. F., " 
 Kent, B. B. .fr., Boston 
 Knapp, A. M., N. Chelsea 
 Knapp, T. T., " 
 
 Lathrop, W. H., Cambridge 
 Leighton, A. W., Boston 
 Learnard, H. E., " 
 Macomber, G. B., " 
 Moody, C. S., S. Hadley 
 Moody, J., " 
 
 Morse, C. F., Hopkinton 
 Osborne, II., Soraerville 
 
 Owens, .T.. Boston 
 Perkins, W. E., " 
 Perkins, H. J., " 
 Pitman, ,1. W. Jr., Maiden 
 PoUitz, J. C, Boston 
 Pope, G., Natick 
 Powell, J. S., Lynn 
 Rice, F. C, S. Boston 
 Russell, C. J., Clincon 
 Ryder, S. N., Boston 
 Saflbrd, De F., Belmont 
 Sant'ord, G. S., Northbridge 
 Simmons, W. A., Chelsea 
 Simpkins, W. H., S. Boston 
 Simpson, A., 
 Sleeper, H., " 
 
 Spier, (,!. C. J., N. Brookfield 
 Stanfield, H. R., Boston 
 Stebbins, H. S., 
 Stover, A. R., 
 Stroens, A., Lawrence 
 
 I Sturgis, F. W., Cambridge 
 
 I Tewl\sbnrv, G. H., I'oston 
 
 I Tweed, W: H., 
 
 I Webber, W. F., 
 Weld, G. M., W. Roxbury 
 Weston, G. l'\, Lincoln 
 Wlieelock, M. G., Clielsea 
 White, T., S. Hadley 
 Woodward, G. M., HoUiston 
 Wright, E. P., Brighton 
 Wright, J. E., Boston 
 Wyer, ,J. J. Jr., Harvard 
 
THC STORE OF THEI 
 
 "QEEEN SIGNS," 
 
 Has established a reputation unequalled in the United 
 
 States for superiority in the manufacture of 
 
 all the numerous styles and kinds of 
 
 ARMY, NAVY, AND CIVILIAN 
 
 M 
 
 M 
 
 t» 
 
 The immense Stock of Cloths on hand, purchased be- 
 fore the heavy advances, offer inducements in prices, 
 leaving no chance for others to underbid. 
 
 I ^» » » 
 
 g n 
 
 The only Corner for these Bargains is the 
 
 CORNER OF ELM STREET, 
 
 No. 13 Dock Square^ 
 
 STORE OF THE " GREEF SI&amp;FS." 
 
 Boston, 1863. 
 
LIBRARY OF CONGRESS 
 
 013 704 
 
 DAVIS &amp; GO. 
 
 PHOTOGRAPHIC ART 
 
 Coraer of WMer ai Wasliingtoii Streets, 
 
 Entrance, No. 2 Winter Street, BOSTON. 
 
 !i lir.illilll 
 159 5 
 
 t\^ Jl r'-y ' 
 
 Photogiaphs of every size and description taken in the 
 best manner ; plain finish, colored, or in India Ink, at prices 
 ranging iVoni $1.00 to $30.00. 
 
 Fine copies of old, or partially faded Daguerreotypes 
 taken. Persons having such daguerreotypes of deceased 
 relatives should have them attended to at once. 
 
 GxlM) PHOTOGRAPHS, 
 
 Now so much in fivor with the public, at $2.50 per dozen, 
 equal, if not superior, to any in this country. 
 
 Have been made at their rooms within the past 9 years, 
 more than one to every house in the New England States. 
 
 Ti^E o:R.ia-iisr.A.x. 
 
 Twenty-Fife Cent Mrctjiie aafi One Dollar Piiotoppli Roonis, 
 
 Corner Winter and Yf asliington Sts., Boston. 
 Advertising and Printing Agency, 
 
 AT 
 
 M, 0. HALL &amp; CQ.'S STATIOIRY STORE, 
 
 No. 23 Cornhill, Boston. 
 
 JOB AND GARB PRINTING 
 
 Neatly executed on New Type. We are ])reinired to execute all orders by Mail or 
 Express, with unequalled despatch. 
 
 j^" Your Orders for Printing are respectfully solicited, and will be executed at 
 satisfactory prices. 
 
 Our facilities for the prompt publication of Advertisements in any papers pub- 
 lished in New England, is not surpassed. 
 
 THOMAS DAVIS ^ COn 
 
 March 4th, 1863. 
 
__EMPTYOCR__JtL 
 
 LIBRARY OF CONGRESS 
 
 B A V I S &amp; G 
 
 PllOTOfiRAPHIi; Al 
 
 Com of Winter ani f asliigoi «ireeis, 
 
 Entrance, No. 2 Winter Street, BOSTON. 
 
 013 704 159 5 
 
 Photographs of every size and description taken in the 
 best manner ; plain finish, colored, or in India Ink, at prices 
 ranging from §1.00 to $30.00. 
 
 Fine copies of ohl, or partially faded Daguerreotypes 
 taken. Persons having such daguerreotypes of deceased 
 relatives should have them attended to at once. 
 
 GAPiB PHOTOGRAPHS, 
 
 Now so much in f ivor with the public, at $2.50 per dozen, 
 equal, if not superior, to any in this country. 
 
 Have been made at their rooms within the past 9 j^ears, 
 more than one to every house in the Now England States. 
 
 Twenty-Fifs Cent Aiiiorolyiis aiid Oiie Dollar Pliotoppli Rooms, 
 
 Corner Winter and Yf ashington Sts., Boston. 
 Advertising and Printing Agency, 
 
 AT 
 
 M, 0. HALL &amp; CQ.'S STATIOMRY STORE, 
 
 No. 23 Cornhill, Boston. 
 
 JOB ASB GARB PRINTING 
 
 Neatly executed on New Type. We are prepared to execute all orders bj' Mail or 
 Express, with unequalled despatch. 
 
 1^° Your Orders for Printing arc respectfully solicited, and will be executed at 
 satisfactory prices. 
 
 Our facilities for the prompt publication of Advertisements in any papers pub- 
 lished in New England, is not surpassed. 
 
 THOMAS DAVIS ^ 
 
 March 4th, 1863. 
 
</field>
<field name="seq">1</field>
<field name="pgnum">0</field>
</doc></add>